My name is Chet Sandu aka the king of
Karach. I smuggled roughly $50 million
worth of illegal steroids from Pakistan
into Europe.
>> My name is David McMillan. I have
smuggled over $17 million worth of
heroin internationally.
>> I'm Roger Reeves. I was a former drug
pilot and sea captain carrying drugs and
I made untold millions.
>> My name is Owen Hansen. I was a football
star at USC and then ran one of the
biggest illegal sports betting
businesses in America.
>> My name is Andrew Pritchard. I was
arrested for smuggling $130 million
worth of cocaine from the Caribbean to
Europe and this is how crime works.
It was becoming an everyday occurrence
that business associates were getting
killed. There has been loads of
occasions when you've actually walked
into a situation and in the back of your
head you're thinking, I might not leave
this room. A person who's addicted to
drugs is addicted to the drugs. A
smuggler is addicted to the lifestyle
and it's almost like a poison in your
blood.
Music played a massive part in my life.
From around 1983 was when I entered into
the sand system culture and I was asked
to play at the parties, produce my sand
system there. I was playing my own gigs
and becoming quite established. It
brought a lot of attention from a lot of
people understanding it was still very
young man at this time 22 years old
making fast amounts of money
entertaining you know thousands and
thousands of people every single
weekend. The drug economy was becoming
massive. Of course, ecstasy, you had a
whole network of people that sold and
distributed those drugs. So, I saw an
opportunity because I realized by
utilizing people I had who were actually
bringing in legitimate cargo, legitimate
goods, which was coming in every day,
mainly perishable goods for quick
clearance and started bringing ecstasy
tablets in that way. Because of the easy
availability from Holland where the
pills were coming in from and the size
of the parties upscaling, it quickly
became a multi-million pound business.
So in 1992, I landed in Jamaica. My mom
came from Jamaica in 1951 and I was born
of the first mixed race generation
posting rush kids. Geographically,
Jamaica is the most wellpositioned
island in the Caribbean sea for
smuggling. One period in the early '9s
they estimated over 10% of all the
cocaine produced in Colombia was trans
shipped through Jamaica. I realized I
had access to customs officers and I had
access to products by the turn
millennium thanks to a great connection
with the Eastern Caribbean cartel. I
moved on to cocaine. a member of my
extended family. Bible I suppose was my
mentor who'd returned to Jamaica and
basically they had been a smuggler but
had retired but was at that time
involved in the dollar exchange business
which basically US dollars of course
were in great demand in Jamaica because
of his contacts in the drug trade meant
that people would come to him in order
for him to exchange their US dollars,
Canadian dollars and pound sterling back
into Jamaican dollars. So he was a
bridge between the underworld and the
you know business people in Jamaica.
Bible let me understand how that
business used to work. You know years
ago he used to bring literally uh tons
of Colombian gold marijuana from
Colombia into the states because there
was a huge demand for it during the 70s.
cocaine started to find its way in in
play and the people who were involved in
the weed smuggling business started to
turn more to cocaine. Bible chosen not
to get involved in its slightest way and
everything he's done on introduction. I
remember a few of the sayings he said
and there was one particular one. It was
never trust the three T's. The three T's
were never talk on the telephone because
obviously the DEA have unlimited access
to tap in phone calls. Never send a text
because all messages in interception is
basically, you know, covered. And never
tell a woman because what sometimes you
can tell someone in the spare of the
moment, it can end up actually getting
you in a life sentence.
But the name which I should say I was
part of was the Eastern Caribbean
Cartel. An Eastern Caribbean cartel sits
in a cluster of the Caribbean islands
and the coast of South America. Cocaine,
you either purchase it from as close to
source as possible, in which case, you
know, it comes in from one of the
islands or you buy it from corrupt Naros
police who are supposed to incinerate
it. But labs generally aren't all mega
labs. They're smaller labs, okay, that
produce a certain amount, 100 a week, 50
a week. It's not as it's made out to be
in films like Scarface. What happens is
if you wanted a consignment, say you
wanted half a ton, 500 kilos. It come
together from three, four, four people
and those people basically wouldn't even
have to go to Colombia. You could
purchase straight from Colombia, but
obviously you are involved in the
process of having to pay FARC who make
sure it gets safely down the waterways.
You know, you've got a whole process of
crossing across again over the border to
Venezuela to jump off point. Back then
you could buy what they call paste,
which is in Colombia, the rawest form of
cocaine approximately $600 a kilo. And
then from the case, it goes through a
process of different chemicals and then
you get it where EH is applied to the
raw product and you're probably getting
cocaine back then for around $900 a
kilo. And then obviously you pay for the
transportation as it crosses various
borders. I would never ever cross to
Colombia because instantly you're blown
up with the DEA um you know watch list.
So I would travel to Guyana. I would
travel to Venezuela reluctantly. Where I
would tend to go would be Tobago because
Tobago obviously sits right beside those
islands but it potentially wasn't on the
DEA watch list as much as the others two
were. They're red red flag countries,
you know, even though Trinidad now is
one of the most red flag countries there
there is.
So most of the shipments either come um
by vessel or they come by plane. So the
generally speaking um ships take between
12 and 14 days to Holland or wherever
you want to go to in Europe. depends on
what rate of seal they burn. It'll come
in what they call dry containers or
refrigerated containers. One thing
people fail to realize is that the
easiest way to smuggle drugs or any form
of contraband is simply by running along
the same side as a route that runs every
single day, which is a normal, you know,
produce or product. Perishable goods,
fruit and veg are a key product to
import. If they're left too long hanging
around, they're going to go rotten. So
these goods are usually cleared very,
very quickly. In UK customs, we have a
series of what they call roots. So for
an example, there's route one, which is
all documentation to be checked, and
that could maybe take 24 hours for a
cargo to be cleared. You've got route
two, which is a physical inspection,
which means all the goods have to be
unpacked. But with companies that have
been running for a long period of time,
they fall under called something called
Route 6, which is instant clearance. So
unless someone phones up the, you know,
the cops and says there's definitely
drugs on there, that shipment will
literally be cleared straight through
customs, no questions asked. For a great
number of years, Splitterfields and
Common Garden Market imported fruit and
veg from virtually every producing
country in the world. You know, making
contact with them as long as I could
guarantee that when products were coming
in for the people who they worked for, I
could definitely get it off at this end
without the actual owner of the company
being any the wiser. So, that was a
system we started to use. I remember
there was a very popular hot sauce brand
and they used to come in boxes like that
of usually 12 or 24 crated and then they
would go into brand cardboard boxes. But
we had a wholesaler in Holland with weed
who literally used to take 20 foot
containers of full of them. And of
course we had syrup and ironically uh we
had a really bad turnout one day because
we had a container loaded. It was about
I think it was close to maybe 4 and a
half metric tons of weed in it. And uh
it never rains in Jamaica. On this
particular day when the container was
being moved to be shipped, it rained and
it rained really really heavily. And one
of the uh guys who was working on the
docks decided he was going to pick up
that container and move it. Put his foot
down, broke into a skid. Of course, the
container was up there on this raft. It
then fell and it was like the gates of
hell as it hit the unforgiving concrete
floor. All dropped out was tons upon
tons of these packages of weed
like a sea of blood basically the red
syrup in with the rain. It was literally
looked like a horror film. The cocaine
the reason why it gets through is
because there aren't enough customs
offices or border force in the world to
check every single piece of cargo. I
remember years ago we used to build
false walls at the back of the
containers, you know, foot and a half
from the back wall. We'd build this
false wall. We'd get some pot rivets. We
put them in vinegar to make them go
rusty and we'd basically put them back
in and fill the back of the container
with weed or cocaine, whatever was
necessarily needed. It meant that by the
time to get in there, they'd have to
obviously unload all the cargo from it.
But of course, then came the um the the
uh the measurable pen where they could
just stick it in there and go bang,
that's 20 foot. You're missing two two
foot at the back of that wall. That was
a very simple, you know, frame of
technology that changed it. And then of
course refrigerator container, you
realize there's a fridge at the back of
it. And when you remove that and look
inside the fridge, it's like a huge
circle, a hole that gets filled with
product. There's been occasion sometimes
things go wrong. I remember one incident
where someone had done plantans, you
know, and what had happened was um the
planters had come through and a woman,
she went and bought a box. She went in
the back of her car and was feeling them
and they were tough. She went back to
the store holder and she's gone, "These
are rubbish. I want my money back." And
he what you're talking about and he's
feeling it and think and he's hit it
against the desk and it's just covered
in white powder like a snowman, right?
is like, you know, full of cocaine. A
week later, a guy, he's turned up, he's
got a brand spanking new Mercedes van,
and they're like, "What?" And he's
saying like he wants to buy a like a
pallet, right? And he's like, he buys
like a two boxes at a time. So,
obviously what happened was he's bought
a few boxes full of cocaine and he's hit
the jackpot and he's thinking, "I'm
going to keep doing it." And that used
to happen a lot. So people randomly
would end up buying their produce for
their shop, going back to their
business, and then lifting a lin of
drugs.
Moving into the world of serious
organized crime is when you then move
into actually paying the people who are
supposed to be policing this stuff,
which are the customs and border force.
So from country of origin in Jamaica,
you would have to pay obviously the
customs in that country, okay? Save
$400,000 for a container full of cocaine
to leave that country of origin. And
that would entail paying the broker who
would do the paperwork, the customs
officers who would be handling the
clearance of the container. He would
maybe involve a dog handler and those
would be your team abroad. Shipping full
stop is international business. However,
every container that leaves the first
thing it does from its country of origin
is allocated a number. So if they're
given that number, they can put an
instant flag on it because it's going to
be inspected here. When they then put it
for inspection, it means they're going
to X-ray it. Now human can override it
by they will identify to go for X-ray
and then the route goes from them to the
um X-ray team X-ray team again they're
paid and they're brought into the
system. They then do their paper
clearance to say it's been X-rayed which
allows a release to go on the container.
He then sends the transport company to
collect the container. container is then
delivered and then driven during the
night usually because obviously the time
that the market opens if it's in the
market down to the market and when it's
taken to the market then it's broken
down and taken where it has to be taken
to a safe house or a slaughter as we
call it and then during the process of
time it's distributed.
The thing about
drugs, particularly cocaine, the UK,
it's a massive marketplace. And when you
import it in volumes, you never really
come in contact with the people who are
actually on the street or on the front
line. So a shipment of half a ton would
probably go to three people and you know
that would be broken up in 200 keys, 200
keys, and 200 keys. Then they would then
distribute it. They'd break it down to
make 30 keys or 50 keys. Then those 50
keys goes down to five keys. And those
five keys then go down to single keys.
And those single keys go down to, you
know, four nine bars. And then four 9 oz
bars then go down to answers. And those
answers then go down to single answer.
Those answers then turn into grams. But
the system with narco economy runs in
different ways and different spaces. One
of the spaces is the social dealer. And
I feel very responsible for the birth of
the social dealer. It started with
ecstasy. During that period, the second
summer of love, people thought it was
acceptable to go and get a few pills for
their friends. They'll start getting 100
pills, sell them in a week, and then
suddenly they lose their jobs. Suddenly
they're paying their car payments and
their mortgage or their rent with the
money from drugs. Then they're a class A
drugs dealer. And that was the birth of
the social drug dealer, which then
turned into cocaine.
getting money back and forth was always
you know something which is the
lifeblood of the business. Things are
different now because people use
cryptocurrency but back then it was
always cash and the methods usually used
were pretty much you know seen in plain
sight. One of them I used to use all the
time we had a guy who had a very large
business basically used to import lries.
We used to firstly buy lries for him
here in which case we put them on the
ship and then he'd pay for the vehicle
when it got to that end. We pay our
people but also we used to actually open
parts of the vehicle, load it with money
basically and then weld it back. When
that money got back to the island
Jamaica it sold on the black market. So
basically money the more you make the
bigger things you find to invest in. So
when you start this kind of business,
what you find yourself is the glitzy
stuff we call it, okay? The shiny stuff.
It's about the jewelry. It's about the
watches. It's about the cars. It's about
stuff you want to say you've got a
status. But then when you move from
there, you kind of go up that ladder a
little bit and you think you suddenly
want to start to invest. You look for
restaurants. You look for things that
you think are quite glamorous,
nightclubs. And these things are like
bottomless pits. They hemorrhage money
if you're not on top of them. However,
the Reddit is this. When it all goes
wrong, everything goes because it's all
traceable. I had lots of different
investments. I invested across real
estate. I invested across property
developments and I wasted a lot of money
on, you know, opportunities or business
investments, you know, couldn't even
sustain themselves.
the drug business full stop became more
and more and more violent particularly
cocaine. People I've done business with
I've seen you know being killed in the
most horrendous ways. Barber introduced
me to a guy called Blacka Duch. And
Blacka was what they call a dawn for an
area in Dante and Kingston. He had
leverage at the docks at the airports.
He was assassinated him and two other
guys you know in broad daylight. two,
three guys drove down into constituency
which um was controlled by another guy
who was described as a dawn, Willie
Huggot. They were there on a corner, car
drove up which they thought was a plane
closed police because plane closed
police in Jamaica wear white shirts and
generally drive tried to coroller
vehicles and they literally just got out
with AK-47s and shuttle through them to
pieces. Another guy I used to work with,
he was shot in the head, put into the
back of a, you know, burning car.
Another guy I knew, a guy walked into a
restaurant where he was in trouble of
people in a crash helmet and started
firing. He got a bullet in the neck. You
know, these were just a few incidents.
When you're in this business, you're in
it and you can't see the wood beyond the
trees. So, what comes with it is all
this stuff. A lot of people who are
involved in the smuggling business in
Jamaica didn't want to get involved in
the cocaine industry because they saw
firsthand what it done to people.
However, there were people who had no
consideration for it. And that
introduced a ruthless element and with
it came bloodshed. And when you talk
about people, you know, who are
dangerous guys, there's a saying in
Jamaica, there's guys in Jamaica that
could scare paint off a building. So
there's people out there that don't fear
anyone or anything, you know, and they
couldn't count how many people they've
killed because one famous saying was,
you know, if you got an Uzi and you're
firing down an alleyway, you're not
counting.
Purity differs because things change and
even from the labs sometimes it isn't
pure and people get it from there and
around Peru in these regions sometimes
better quality is coming from there.
It's really strange because I've never
sold a product I haven't taken. Hence
I've never sold heroin. I've taken
cocaine. I've taken ecstasy. I've smoked
marijuana. But one ironic thing is when
I've actually been involved in smuggling
them, I haven't wanted to use them.
Quality is the most important thing like
anything with drugs. If you buy
something cheap, it's not going to last
and it's difficult to sell. My strategy
that I took on board was stack them high
and sell them cheap. So I buy the best,
but buy lots of it and sell it cheap.
People talk about, you know, uh pink
Peruvian champagne and all these other
stuff. What people fail to realize is
the reason why these forms of cocaine
are pink or an off color is because
they're unable to get the chemicals.
They'll use substitute chemicals for it.
You know, the easiest way of telling
good cocaine, it's oil. So, you just put
it in your thumbs and let it dissolve.
If it's good, you know, you should be
able to the sight and smell should
straight away let you know the quality.
I used various methods of transport for
smuggling. A lot in the early days was
done by plane, baggage handers, things
like that. Of course, you could always
do good consignments in the cargo areas.
However, most of the big stuff was
really done by containers because these
were hugely profitable. If it's coming
through the airport, it's coming in
smaller quantities. However, you still
got to pay a series of people. You have
to have a check-in assistant who's going
to be able to log it on there. You have
to obviously have the dog handler who's
going to obviously let that go through.
And then depending where you're then
going on from that point, if it's going
to be an X-ray and they turn a blind eye
to the X-ray, they've got to be paid. Me
and my business partner were at in
Jamaica and we've stayed at the Windham
Hotel. But during that period of time,
the English cricket team were actually
touring the West Indies to play. They
were there sitting by the pool with us
and we're watching every single day
these big flight cases with the cricket
bats coming in and out. and was sitting
there thinking
those flight cases are not going to be
checked. So what we'd done is we'd teed
it up with one of the guys who was at
the hotel that we'd be able to access
those flight cases and pack them with
cocaine. The only problem we then had
was Jamaica wasn't the last test. So
not being one to give up easily, I
thought there's got to be another
system. And one of the guys that came
out there to meet us, he happened to
mention that there are certain things
that couldn't be x-rayed. And one of
them was computer screens. And we
thought, hold on, if they can't be
x-rayed,
you can probably put anything in them
you want. And of course, what we had was
a really good contact in Venezuela who
actually was involved in computer parts.
And over [snorts] a period of 6 months,
we just gradually became a steady
importer of computer scrims for
Venezuela. Of course, this helped us
considerably with cash flow for events
and all the other stuff we were doing
within the computer screens. We had
created a balloon which was packed with
cocaine. Some of the ones we'd used over
the years were suitcases and one in
particular one was the body which we
called the stiff. I'd noticed that
someone had actually tried to send a
body um with a coffin full with drugs in
it, but they failed because it was
randomly opened at the airport. Of
course, that problem wasn't going to
have because we had our people who
worked at the airport. In Jamaica, it
was quite easy to get access to people
like, you know, who knows someone. So,
getting a doctor was real simple. Um the
biggest thing was obviously being able
to get the authorization to ship a body.
So, for example, you knew a guy, he was
a drug addict or if he was an alcoholic,
he'd sell you his passport for 500 quid.
So, the picture just could be simply
cut, lifted, put whatever picture you
want in it, and went into the Jamaican
High Commission to tell him he died. The
doctor we had, we paid him a few
hundred. He issued a death certificate.
Of course, you know, no sight of body,
nobody existed. took the death
certificate up to the high commission
with the passport and subsequently got
access to ship the body over. And of
course once we had the shipping
arrangements put in place we had a local
undertakers who reverently retrieved the
body from the airplane and that was one
incident.
I had a great love for AfroCaribbean
music dominantly reggae and soul and I
set up a sand system with couple of
friends from my road. What was the
turning point was the winter of 1988.
We came across a huge warehouse. Paid
the guy would been the equivalent of
maybe $800 US at night for the for the
be venue and started to stage parties.
By New Year's Eve, the events were being
flooded by celebrities. People like Boy
George, Mini Vanilli. Top ranking
artists were turning up to party and
enjoy themselves. And that was a massive
launch pad for a company I'd put
together called Genesis. When you're
putting on parties of that scale, you
tend to meet a lot of people and you
seem to climb a pecking order in
Britain's underworld. Nightife and
gangsters go together. When the parties
seemed to be coming to an end under
pressure from police raids, the drug
economy was becoming massive. Ecstasy
was a drug which in Holland it was legal
until 1988. It was illegal here earlier
under the misuse of drug act, but people
were still relatively flexible about the
drug. In Britain, tablets were sell up
to £25, you know, a single pill and they
could be wholesaliled for up to 20
pounds. And that time they were being
bought in Holland for around about 12 or
13 pounds. But as demand came more and
more and more and more people took them,
the price started to drop. Eventually I
could buy pills in Holland for £3 a
tablet and I could get them here and
actually wholesale them anywhere
between6 and8 a tablet by the,000. So
there were huge profit margins and
every£10,000 you're making £30,000 or
£50,000.
things were, you know, going like
clockwork. But like all the best laid
plans, eventually something will go
wrong. One morning I received the phone
call. Someone said to me, uh, you know,
there's a serious incident at what I
call a safe house. They said, uh,
basically the police were all over it.
So in January 1992, via a false
passport, I was on the run and I landed
in Jamaica.
The idea of going to Jamaica was for me
to keep low. Unfortunately, I didn't
know what the word low profile meant. I
was introduced to a circuit of people of
quite high society Jamaican and I met a
young lady whose father was a prominent
Jamaican politician. Uh she fell
pregnant and during this time while I
was seeing her she fell pregnant. I also
met another young lady who instantly
took my breath away, Miss Jamaica Weld.
I also ended up having a child with her,
which I have two beautiful sons as a
result of. But of course, I put myself
from a lowprofile character into the
front page of Jamaican news. So, imagine
it. I'm 25 years old and I'm trying my
hardest to go straight. Me being me, the
marriage fell apart and you know I found
myself on a road to chaos. I got myself
into a fight, ended up in a Jamaican
prison and as luck would have it have
family that could help influence
situations and managed to bribe my way
out of there. Around about 1997
um I finally put the dots together. I
was around my friends again, people I'd
grown up with. A lot of those guys had
now climbed the criminal ladder.
Naturally, Jamaica was a producing
country where cannabis grows. So, Bible,
my mentor, he had an amazing list of
contacts and they trusted him because he
was a very superior figure. He was able
to at least give me the protection that
I needed. Barber introduced me to a guy
called Blackadoo. He showed me how the
mechanics worked of the business. You
know, we take drives down to the
country, which would be like St.
Elizabeth, where weed is grown, and
farmers then would come with their
harvest of weed. The stuff would be
taken, it would be bagged, it would be
obviously weighed and then paid for.
Then camp, makeshift camps would be set
up in what we call the bush. So, we used
to be out there and people basically
would set up two pieces of railroad
track which would create a press in the
middle of it. Special metal plates were
made and big tarpolons were put on the
floor. Women would take sharp little
knives, manicure the weed, taking out
the seeds, separating the seeds from the
buds. They were all then put into these
um um presses, these blocks, and then
compressed down. Then they were wrapped
with various sheets of um you know,
cellophane, and then we put what we call
dog repellent on them, which is made of
leaves of different trees. And then the
tri the weed was then transported down
into central Kingston where it would be
leaving from. It was a very very
profitable business. So on average you
could purchase the best marijuana for
around $70 a kilo. Once it gets back to
England the same weed would fetch
anywhere up to $3,000 a pound. So the
profit margins was huge, even larger if
you look on the scale of it than
cocaine. getting the product in
consignments down from the country into
central Kingston where it's going to
ship from. That would usually be done on
a on a cane rafter. Police did stop it
randomly. They're certainly not going to
unload with sugarcane. Sometimes with
ambulances, so we'd obviously pay an
ambulance driver and he would basically
put it on. He'd basically blue light it
all the way down. Even police we used to
used to drive it down. you know, it was
a very smuggler friendly uh place when I
lived there.
One thing about making money is great,
but doing something that you are
passionate about doing was really
important to me. And having grown up in
a sand system culture and I'd done
warehouse parties, but one thing I
hadn't done, I hadn't done major
concerts or festivals. And the jewel in
the crown for any reggae enthusiast was
reggae sunsplash that I just might be
able to achieve bringing it back to the
UK. So in 1999 we put on one of the most
amazing events ever seen. But again
unfortunately being the person I am and
the business we were running had a lot
of attention drawn to it. In particular
people who were coming to visit us at
the office. Some of these people were on
the police radar. There was one
particular individual who was having
stolen cars, taking apart and exporting
them and he used to have some beautiful
cars he'd bring by to the office on
occasions and ironically work Jean was
headlining the reggae son special event
and we had one of our drivers driving
him around in the vehicle when he was
here which of course unbeknown to us was
a stolen car. One morning the serious
crime squad decided to crash my house
when I was in bed. uh they arrived and
subsequently they
discovered that vehicle on the drive.
They also discovered um a number of
different um documents basically related
to stolen cars and they also discovered
a small quantity of drugs. I was
arrested and obviously I was back to
square one again. But as luck would have
it, I'd realized they'd actually
released me from bail and they hadn't
charged me. By the beginning of November
that year, I'm back in Jamaica. I
plunged myself deeply into the world of
smuggling. So, as much as I have
passions for other things, every single
time I done them to levels of success,
smuggling would always represent itself
back into my life and basically destroy
whatever positive attributes I had
started.
So, it's 2004. I had a contact who I
worked with in the underworld and he
came to me and said that he had access
to a team of officers who were clearing
containers. And at first obviously I was
very sort of you know that doesn't seem
right. How do you get a whole team? Did
seem like a bit too good to be true. And
what had happened was um a guy who had a
former military background, special
units, people who are trained in you
know um high levels SAS, people like
that are sometimes given jobs with the
police to do surveillance. This
individual would actually been offered a
job with what they call a ghost unit in
customs and excise. And the job he was
entitled to do was actually look out for
corrupt customs officers. Rather than
collecting the evidence obviously and
taking it to his superiors, he
approached them directly and said to the
officers who he had information on, I've
got this on you and this is the deal.
This either goes to the superior and
you're going to probably end up in jail
or face charges or be sacked or if you
want I can show you how to work and you
work with me by getting access to these
officers who he was investigating. He
had obviously access now to us which was
an organized crime group. So he
facilitated himself as the overall
fixer. So what would happen is he'd
charge a million pounds a container that
was a flat rate regardless of what was
in the container. He'd be give us
specific instructions of what we'd have
to do. We want x amount of money up
front which was only a small holding
deposit £100,000
and then after that all the balance must
be paid within 48 hours of receiving a
container. Now, a million pounds or $1.5
million US could have seemed like quite
a lot of money to some people, but when
you're talking about bringing in drugs,
you're talking about tiny money, it's
pittance. We started to organize
something. We put on, you know, I think
it was like 500 kilos of cocaine on the
first shipment and bang, cleared it.
Came straight through. Not an issue. And
it was like it's real. It it works. Give
us the um container number as soon as it
leaves the country of origin. So we had
a code we created which was numbers and
letters which was sort of done in
reverse. And then once the container
then was ready for release, we had to go
in normal procedure with paperwork and
he'd then contact our guy and our guy
would say it's ready to collect. So now
we'd discovered and had access to the
best thing in the world. You were given
an opportunity to ship what you want in
any quantity you want, you know, clean
as a whistle. And one of the team I
worked with, an associate.
At this point, I said, "Listen, we stop
everything and we just specifically do
this." But what happened was he actually
was putting himself around and offering
services to a lot of other people. Now
understand in the east of London and
Essex and Kent as well, you've got a lot
of groups of people who are prolific
smugglers who are also working through
the market. He had actually been working
with a team and they were bringing in
pineapples but in disguise. So, they've
been hollowing out the pineapples,
putting cocaine in there, sealing them
with wax, putting them back, and
basically sending them over. But the
police were actually looking at this uh
group of people. So, one of my
associates that work at the market, he
was under surveillance because he'd been
working with his team from Essex. So,
their mobile phones are all being
tapped. They were on regular
surveillance. In December 2004, a
container carrying 584 kgs of cocaine
concealed in saxus coconuts arrived at
Spitterfields market. When the container
arrived with the produce in it, I called
him. I said, "It's cleared. It's ready
to collect." Anyway,
his phones was under surveillance.
Customs was thinking, "Hold on, how can
it be cleared when these pineapples are
still on the water?" So they had
absolutely no idea whatsoever about the
co the coconut shipment. The officers
who were investigating the pineapples
after hearing the container had been
cleared drove down to the docks. So
randomly they decided to pull the
container. They opened the container and
half a ton of cocaine literally fell out
the back onto them all. If they were to
have arrested the customs officers,
suspended them or investigated any way
whatsoever, which they should have done,
we instantly would had a loophole. But
not only us having a loophole, every
single container that had gone through
there with drugs in it and everyone that
had been arrested for those drugs over
years, all those people that were in
prison serving time for it would have
meant every single case would have had
an appeal because the evidence that
they'd given in court couldn't have been
trusted. They were told to turn the
blind eye and send us to collect it. The
following evening we went to the market.
By this time the cocaine had been
replaced with blocks of wood. Um the all
the blocks of wood now were in the were
in the in the container. customs pounced
and everyone was arrested.
And it was basically a cut and dry case
because for all intents and purposes,
they made the biggest seizure at the
time of cocaine in in London. There'd
never been a seizure of that size ever
before. And you know, we were carted off
to prison um awaiting obviously trial.
So, it's December
2004.
Myself and six codefendants have all
been arrested and we're all now locked
up on remand at Onsworth Prison. Four
being knowingly concerned in impulation
of 584 kg of cocaine. So, basically, it
wasn't looking good. I remember when I
um saw my solicitor come to visit me in
a prison. I said to him, you know, I
said, "It's, you know, it's a bad
corner. I know it's a bad corner. You
know, how's it looking?" He said, "As
long as you got a hole in your ass, I
can get out of this one." So basically
the evidence against us was four years
of surveillance coming from the DEA
Interpol serious crime directive 7 uh
metro middle market um uh police and
regional crime squad. There virtually
wasn't an intelligence source that
hadn't been gathering information on us
over a period of years which had been
compiled into public interest immunity.
They had in the police lock up over 500
kg of pure cocaine. They had an
abundance of, you know, um, cash, other
things they'd managed to seize from the
raids which they conducted straight
after. It put bluntly was not looking
good. So I was approached in prison by
another inmate who said to me he had
access to a corrupt officer that was
aware of the case and he had access to
all my case documents. So the same
corrupt officer was prepared for a quart
of million pounds to go into customs
house go into the safe under a different
identity and steal all the documents. I
was then slipped these documents in
prison. So what I realized as soon as I
saw them, they were all highly sensitive
intelligence service documents. I
thought to myself, this could be my
golden ticket. All I had to do was find
a method of devising bringing these
documents into the court to cause enough
of a benefit of that. So imagine these
documents, my legal team couldn't see
them. The only person who actually was
allowed them was the judge and the
prosecution. I managed to get him into
court and literally cause bedum. All
bets were off. It caused complete
madness. The judge was going ballistic,
but it created enough confusion to force
a retrial. There's a retrial. Of course,
this won't fall for the same trick
twice. So, I'm searched before I go into
court, but I've preempted that's going
to happen and arranged a pirate radio
station broadcast the contents of the
documents on the station. second
retrial, all seven of us were acquitted.
So May 2007, I'm released from custody.
You know, taken a different direction in
my life. My son Hayden is born and now
I'm ready to go straight and live a
normal life. But as they say, the road
to hell is paved with good intentions. I
decided it was time to go back to the
music industry. Wasn't really getting me
the same kind of financial gains that
drug smuggling was getting me. So, I got
back involved in the business. I made a
lot of money in a very short period of
time. That's where it all started to go
wrong. Someone I knew who was a local
guy to me, I lent some money to help him
out of a situation. And unfortunately,
he'd been under police surveillance.
There was no hope of me getting my money
back. I was game to get involved. So, I
arranged a shipment, but wanted to be
nowhere near it. On the day of this
product arriving, I was told I had to go
with him to collect it. Now, I'm coming
from the old school of gangsters. So, I
agreed I'll do it. But this is the
arrangement. If police turn up or come
anywhere near you, what I'll do is I'll
be behind you and then any police
stopping you or trying to stop you, I'll
take them out the road and you just
carry on driving, take off and get rid
of the gear. But unbeknown to me, he'd
been a police magnet. So he was either
doing one of two things. He was either
giving information deliberately to the
police, but more likely I felt he had
the idea of taking drugs off of people
and then not having to pay him because
they were getting arrested. So all he
had to do was lead the police straight
to him. The most bizarre thing was when
the police did put on their sirens and I
done what I said I was going to do and
decided to take my Range Rover and force
them off of the road. He just literally
slows down and pulls up with 6 kg of
cocaine in the back seat. So there I am,
arrested,
track record, been acquitted of 500
kilos plus seven years earlier, and I'm
centered now with driving a police car
off of the road with drugs in that car.
It ain't looking good. After two trials
in 2014, I end up getting 15 years and
become a category prisoner.
It took a lot for me to wake up to
reality. But when I faced reality, I was
at Belm Marsh prison and I could see all
these young guys and I saw them doing
huge sentences. Their lives were wasted.
And the realization came to me. They're
killing each other on the streets. And
my parents were community leaders. They
were people who done everything they
could to build communities. And for all
these years, I'd been destroying them
for my own self-gratification
for things which I thought were so
important to have possessions. And the
realization came to it, you know, I had
blood on my hands. So my mission in life
had to be how can I do something to
rectify some of the I've done in my life
and turn stuff around and allow my
conscience finally to become my guide.
People
get arrested and they say, "Ah, poor
me." And they start to feel sorry for
themselves, but they don't give
consideration for the victims. I never
gave consideration for any victims. I
asked myself the question, would I want
any of my children to go down this road?
The answer is no. But more importantly,
would I want anyone else's child to go
down this road? And the answer to that
is no. In 2019, I was finally released
from prison and started the AP
Foundation. The most important thing for
me was to be able to put my life down
in words. To let people be able to read
on it and reflect on it, not as a vanity
project, but to serve as a lesson, to
serve as something to understand that
when it all comes to the end, when it
turns the final chapter, was it all
worth it? And the answer to that is no.
You have to go on a journey sometimes,
but the in destination sometimes or most
times isn't quite what you thought it
would be. So, I wrote my autobiography,
Empire of Dirt, to explain and
understand what it is. When it comes
down to it, you're just building an
empire of dirt. It has no substance or
real value compared to the value of
people, relationships.
To this day, the most common um route of
shipping cocaine is container ships. But
it's not just limited to container
ships. What the biggest one they do is
the deep sea fisher fishing tankers. So
they'll bring those in huge nets.
They'll be full of gear. They'll put a
uh like the satnav thing that they use
for the ship and they'll drop them. And
then what happens is they'll drop them
on the coast and then the smaller
fishing trollers around these series
talking about will go in and retrieve
them. Subs have been going for a long
while now for as long as actually I can
remember from the 90s. You know go fast
boats are still very much in use. you
know, um to do the short runs. Um you
know, all the traditional methods, uh
diving ships is very common where people
put what we call a torpedo at the bottom
of it, which is a large package of drugs
and then divers go in to retrieve it
after it's arrived. Prices will only go
down if there's a bigger supply and a
bigger demand. And prices have dropped
considerably. Seizures now are bigger
than they used to be. So perhaps we have
a very small idea of what actually is
being produced or what's actually
getting through to what it really really
is. So we're moving away from where half
a ton was a lot of drugs. We're talking
about shipments of 5 10 tons now coming
through on a very regular basis and
getting caught. I think what's going on
at the moment with fast boats being
attacked and people being shot on them,
it's something obviously which is done
for a scare tactic. But people have to
realize this. For someone to get on a
fast boat with four 250 Yamaha engines
and a massive tank of petrol on it
filled with cocaine, you're pretty
desperate in the first place. So the
people that are getting shot here and
getting killed are people at the very
bottom of the ladder. They're very
easily replaced. So it's not going to
stop anything. Drugs could be, and I say
this as a form of drugs, a scourge on
society because when you honestly look
what it does to people,
it destroys them. But it doesn't just
kill them. It's what dies inside of them
when they're alive. We should actually
look and say to ourselves, maybe we
should spend a bit more time and money
researching it. Maybe some drugs should
be legalized. Maybe some drugs should be
looked at, you know, the purposes some
drugs do have. For example, marijuana to
help people with asthma and other
conditions. We now know it helps in
cancer in some cases and situations.
Maybe we should rethink it. Everyone
wants to find themselves in the
marketplace, okay? You know, mainland
Turkey was obviously a dominant place of
heroin. We all know this. Now, the
relationship obviously with cocaine
being exchanged for heroin and you know,
Turkish syndicates having more influence
as in Albanian syndicates having more
influence. So, the dynamics changes
every so often and it will be different
in another five years. Kids are on the
street dying, you know, for washed rock
and they're putting their life on the
line. And there are guys out there going
to prison for selling grams. But when
Middle England and the society that
turns around and gives out these big
sentences stop making those phone calls
after dinner because they want a social
gram for the dinner party. And when that
stops, that's when we can start to look
about stopping the problem. But it's
supply and demand. Upper class people
have glamorized cocaine to make it
something that poor people want. And
what's the real shame is the people who
really are at the helm of giving out
huge sentences to the people who are the
kids who are probably selling drugs um
you know um to put some food on the
table for their mom or to you know get
the basic bits and pieces that they
want. Not necessarily. So all of them,
but a lot of them they're in caught in a
poverty belt are delivering the cocaine
to upper class, middle class people who
are a lot of them are in a criminal
justice system as lawyers. A lot of them
are accountants. A lot of them are high,
you know, level jobs making a lot of
money and it's amusement for them. But
every gram of cocaine they put up their
nose is blood that they are putting on
the street with kids who are fighting
over those deals, who are fighting over
those turfs.
>> My name is Chet Sandu aka the king of
Karach. I smuggled roughly $50 million
worth of illegal steroids from Pakistan
into Europe. This is how crime works.
There's about a million people in the UK
that use steroids. It was just like a
money-making machine for me. If you go
to a doctor for it, they won't give you
that. So, you have to go legally. So,
smuggling, bringing it in, uh, that was
the only option. I was bringing in by
large amounts cuz the need for it, the
demand was massive.
There are steroids in the UK that can be
prescribed by a doctor. Uh but they will
give you a manual amount. But if you
want to import, sell, do anything else
with them, give them to other people,
that's totally illegal. That comes in a
conspiracy to supply drugs. Well, the
first time I started to sell steroids
was probably about 1994. I was working
as door security um in a bar in
Newcastle. And then that's where I got
to know people in the gym, people the
dorman, the security, they all want to
be big. They were all taking steroids
and people wanted the proper source
there. They wanted the the real deal. I
thought, okay, this is what they want.
And there's a niche in the market here
because there was a lot of people that
couldn't even get their hands on it. I
had to go to the source and that was to
Karach. Uh cuz that was the address on
the label of the box that I used to buy
in England. The Karachi scale probably
started from about 96 97. I'm Indian so
I need a visa to go to Pakistan. We go
there for a week and we we would source
the drugs somehow and we would bring
them back. So we traveled there um
booked into a hotel but there
prostitutes were there. Yeah. On the
eighth floor where we were staying and I
used to talk to them and they said what
you need to do is go to this
marketplace. But these people have links
with al-Qaeda, Taliban, uh the police.
They're all paid off. They're all They
all get a bit of the money. So, they're
allowed to move drugs in them large
amounts. So,
I went to the shop. Uh there was just
like a market stall shop. There was two
guys outside was with shotguns
and I thought this quite strange this a
chemist and they've got guns outside. So
the boss called me in told me to have a
seat and then he was asking me stuff uh
where am I from and this and that. So I
explained to him what what I wanted. He
right okay gave us a price but what was
it 30 grand? He says I have the real
deal for 30 p an ampule or I can give
you snide fake for 10 p an ampule and
they come exactly the same. They look
exactly the same. I said no no no. I
said I just want the real deal. I gave
him the money. What he did, he didn't
even count it. He just tapped on the
ceiling of the roof. Uh, one of them
squares opened up and there was a kid up
there. He gave him the money and he ran
off and that was that. And he says,
"Yeah," he was called. He says, "Come
here back in the morning. It'll be here
for you 11:00 and bring two taxis," he
said. And we went back and everything
was uh ready just like he said. And I
only stuck with that one supplier the
whole time. He backed me up. He helped
me out. Gave me some good links. And
they even spoke to the chief of police
for me as well.
The steroids um they were all coming
from registered factories. These
factories are officially open. It's like
uh FISA he used to sell their products.
The supplier worked with a few factories
because he had every spectrum of
pharmaceutical drugs that you can think
of. Uh the companies he was working with
rush rush is a big firm. Rash was like a
big supplier of pills to Pakistan. I did
ask him do you supply these steroids to
anybody else in the UK on this level?
And he said no. He said it's only you.
The only people that were selling it
were like some white guys. But I know
white guys can't go to Karach and do
what I just did because firstly they
don't know their language and they
wouldn't trust them and uh it just
wouldn't work. So um that's how I knew
he wasn't really dealing on a high level
with anybody else from from the UK
anyway. Normally steroids have a certain
smell to them because I've smelt every
steroid there is. They have that same
order. That's how I know always. Yeah. I
always smell it. Sometimes I've smelt it
and it's been weak. So that I would
suggest is just filled up with cooking
oil. So fake products are getting moved.
I just had the finished product at the
end of the day. But I knew that was from
a good source. These steroids, they're
like made they're made officially
hologrammed packaging how to take. They
come with all the instructions inside
the side effects. It's like a full
doctor prescription thing. It's like
everything. Have you ever seen a lab in
the UK?
>> Uh, yes. I've seen a Back Street garage
lab of this guy. He had the oils. He was
just getting them in these big container
things. The quality of the steroid was
rubbish. And he was putting it in the 10
mil multi-shots himself. Uh, he puts it
in himself, seals it himself.
And so this is where you can get
bacteria, anything can go into these
balls. And this is where people were
getting absesses um and other things
were happening to them because it's not
made in a clean environment. The quality
of what my friend was selling and the
quality of what I was bringing in there
were two extreme levels. Um because the
quality of what he was doing it was
probably it was very very weak and you
don't know what's in it. When we got the
steroids they're all packed
individually. They all came like a
little box, like a matchbox, and there's
one ampule in each one of these things.
But how we had to bring them back, we
had to get one of these boxes and put
six ampules in each box. And so it was
condensed by six vials in a small box.
At first, we did this ourselves. Uh
attempted it by getting each bottle out
and packing it and packing it, but there
was 50,000 ampules and uh this was like
it was taken as ours. So, um, I spoke to
my taxi driver about it. Went to his
village where he was from. He got about
12 boys there. Sat them all down in his
house. So, he got it all, the 50,000
amps packed up. And I paid him, I think
about £300. That was like a month's wage
to get that all packed down. After that
experience, I told the supplier that I
had a problem with the packaging. And he
says, "Okay, let me do it." I disguised
them in vitamin B12 tubs, but he
organized that on the second trip
onwards
to smuggle the steroids back. They would
just all be packed down. Uh I think it
was 23 to 24 kilo I was allowed to take
back in one case. I thought, okay, let's
just take it through through the airport
because it's not illegal here in
Pakistan. So I'm thinking we'll bribe
him. Uh that was my that was my initial
thought. The first time going through
airport security. Yeah that was nervous.
The first security were there and they
said okay open up the cases. We opened
them up. Some of them didn't even know
what it was you know steroids. They were
looking at it going. Okay f what is it?
But why have you got all this amount and
there too much of it as well? Three
suitcases full. I got through that bit
because there was some adult magazines
in the case, right? And one of the
security, he picked her up in the year
1996 in Pakistan. You can't get like
adult magazines there. You can't get it.
It's it's illegal. So, we gave him the
magazines and then they let us go
through the first part of security. And
then I had to go to the X-ray machine.
They x-rayed it and then they went,
"Right, open it up." So, the same
process again, but with them again. I
bought them off with the magazines. That
was my first time round. The second time
round, uh, they knew who I was. I had to
pay them off the first security ones and
then I had to pay the ex the X-ray ones.
I think I gave them, it was UK pound
notes, £40 each
on the security, 40 to50. And then it
was only on the third trip where the
chief narcotics officer at Karach
airport approached me. He said you just
pay me a100 pound a suitcase and I will
and I will guide you through. So on that
trip when I went back he met me at the
airport and I just bypassed all security
all the x-ray machines all this he just
told his people his porters get their
bags and take them all the way through.
the bags are on the flight. Uh we change
Amsterdam and um the bags go from that
plane onto another plane and then from
Amsterdam to Newcastle. It's a 5:00 a.m.
flight. Uh there's no security there at
Newcastle customs ever at that time. The
people involved in smuggling operation
was like me and two mules I would take
with me. I would just pay them £1,000 uh
pay for all the holiday just all the
food, drinks, expenses. I I pay that. So
for them, they're just getting like a
free trip away for a week. So that was a
system I had. And I would change my
mules as well. It would be people who I
knew, people who I knew from my
hometown. Um trusted people sort of
thing who could keep their mouth shut.
back then there was a a surplus amount
of people who would be willing to do
that because um the jail for it in
England was class C uh which is I think
a maximum is three years so the
sentencing on that you know it wasn't
like uh cocaine or ecstasy I walked
through and there was nobody there was
no airport security there and I was
thinking wow got through after I bring
in the steroids uh into the UK Then the
marketing starts.
I would approach either dealers in
Scotland, uh, Manchester and Liverpool,
and I would sell to them in bulk. They
would buy off me 10,000 ampules at a
time. And plus, I sold steroids singly
as well for the top value for £4 an
ampule. Uh, I got the top price because
people would come to me and just buy 10
at a time. Nobody else would take a cut
of any of this. Um, because it was all
done quite easily. Um, if I moved it in
bulk in large amounts, it goes quite
quickly. I would serve up like people I
knew, my dormant friends, people at the
gym, security,
um, other gyms, they all got served up
with with with my supply. It's quite
open that sometimes I've seen in gyms
where people have just gone into the
changing room and they've just started
injecting each other. I would always
inject at home but I but I have injected
in a gym. I've even injected on stood
outside the door of a club as well.
Security just even there as well big
gyms are complicit. Yes. Um they would
really turn a turn a blind eye to it.
Yeah. Because they know these people if
they weren't taking steroids they're not
going to come and train. So it's hand in
hand. you know, you want these people in
here because they're paying the monthly
fees and they're using all this and
they're paying them money, uh, but
they're using steroids at the same time.
So, if you stop them from using steroids
or try and stop them from using
steroids, they won't go to your gym.
Yeah. And, um, in smaller gyms, I've
seen people uh, the owners and they're
quite open with it. I've seen them just
talk out loud in front of people, I've
got this, I've got that. Um,
this is available. How it used to work
was um I never used to ask the gym
owners if they wanted the steroids. They
used to approach me. They used to ask me
because they knew I had a quality
product. It was good and it was on a
sound and reliable and based as well
like the stock will always be there but
mainly they would just let it go just
let it happen. As long as it's not
directly in front of everybody just do
what you want. people that moved on from
legal use to illegal use. I do know
people who have approached their doctors
and they've asked them for uh
testosterone and I think I think I
remember one person he got something but
uh it was only like a 100 milligram if
there's a big seizure made uh normally
things can go dry in that area. um and
they things can go dry and then the
stock isn't there and then people will
if they can't get the best stuff they
will get the stuff that's not that well
made but I was just doing it on a
constant flow so it never went dry.
I did these runs um it lasted about a
year and a half um until it came on top
and I was doing it every six weeks
roughly. I was just thinking myself as a
I'm an extra person and I can take back
I can make off a bag 20 grand. You know
60 grand of three bags is what 20 grand
a bag I'm making. So I wasn't going to
let the opportunity go down
greedy. I was in a way. The cost of my
trip will be like this. There'll be
three tickets bought. They're about £350
each. The hotel I would pay for two
rooms, one for me, one for the mules.
That wouldn't be much in Pakistan. That
was only about I think 2030 pound a
night. I used to give everybody drinks
out. So you would spend money there as
well, you know. You would give them
money. You would give out tips. I gave a
lot of people tips as well, which I
didn't need to do, but I did that just
to keep people happy because I'm doing
bad in their country. And the officers,
yes, I used to pay them as well, £300 on
them on each case. So that will be on
top about two and a half thousand two
and a half thousand pound for uh 60
grand return. I've made millions and
I've lost millions. I bought myself a
few things, jewelry, uh clothing, cars.
I spent a lot of money on I had a lot of
nice cars. You buy cars, but I crashed a
lot of cars as well. While the money's
rolling in, it's all good fun. Um
there's a lot of people want to jump on
the train. Uh but when the train stops,
they all jump off the train. men and
they don't even come near you after
that. Uh they're all there for the ride,
but once uh the money stops, the jail
comes and then that's when reality it
kicks in.
The steroids I was bringing in at the
time were sustenon um which was a mix of
testosterone. So there was a uh tester
decanate, propinate, sipinate. Um it's
just a mixture of uh tests what last a
different length of time. The main forms
is tablet form. Uh but they go through
your liver and kidneys. The tablet form
people have seem to gone off the tablet
form but some people like to take a
tablet form. You can still get the
Anapolon uh Anava, which is a a steroid
what girls take because it's the mildest
steroid you can take and it has the
least amount of side effects. In ampule,
uh you get different ones. Um they
normally come in 1 mil. You can get 1
mil amps or 2 mil amps. It depends on
the steroid, but you can buy
>> [snorts]
>> uh a 10 shot mini one as well, mini
vials. Yeah, you get 10 one mil shots
out of that. Uh they just have a plastic
stopper on. You put the needle through
and you draw back. Um you get 10 10 in
one of them. So that's how they're
normally sold. There's some people that
that will abuse it. Um there some people
that could take about 20 injections a
week. Uh three injections a day, which
is what I used to do. There was a time
where like I was injecting that much. I
needed new sort of injecting sites. Um,
I've injected my biceps before, my
triceps, my chest even once, uh, my
thighs, my ass, anywhere where there's
like a big muscle. If you're looking for
new sites all the time, and then
obviously you're abusing it. Steroid
use, misuse. Um, yes, it is a medical
matter.
Yes, I was addicted to steroids when I
was uh taking them in my peak. I only
used to be about 12 stone. 12 stone. I
couldn't get past that no matter what I
did, no matter how hard I trained. And
then I went up to 17 and a half stone
from 12 to 17 and a half. And my bench
press was 200 kilo 200 kilo bench. There
weren't many people in my town who could
do that who had that sort of power and
strength that that that I had. And I
think I was addicted to that. I was
addicted to having that power and
strength. And if I stopped hitting the
steroids, that power and strength's
going to go away. the look of me is not
going to be as good. It's not going to
be as intimidating. It's not going to be
I will lessen I will go lesser lesser
lesser if I stop taking it. Uh that's my
belief. Yes. So an addiction.
Yes. Because I was addicted to that and
I wanted to stay that way. If you have
enough on you what they suspect you are
supplying and you are making money off
this uh you can go to jail. Yeah. Up to
up to 14 years in the US.
I was arrested in Spain Aleante in uh
1999.
The amount I had I think was a quarter
of a million pills and 50,000 ampules.
That's what I had on me. We landed at
Alicanti airport. Me and the two mules.
I was stood on my own. The two mules
were stood on their own. Uh the baggage
was going round and round. Our cases
never never came through.
So then I knew something was up and it
was then when I knew I think it was here
and then the guard of Seville come
around the corner with guns and there
went bomb sandu on the floor handcuff
me. I was devastated and I just looked
over at the two mules that I bought and
I just felt bad for them. Um I just saw
instantly then I seen it in their faces
like bam. It just dropped me. I knew
what I was doing and uh they didn't know
what they were doing. They didn't know
that this was going to happen, that this
could happen. I knew, you know, um but
uh it was just a sinking feeling. And
then they took us away.
They took us to Funkent
Funk Alicante. We're just in the middle
of mountains. Nothing else around it.
It's just like a jail amongst mountains.
Uh they took us in. It looked scary to
me. We were just held there on remand
for over two years. Um our court date
had not come because uh the police were
trying to find out if I had money in
Spain. They went, "You're going to Mudu
one." And they went, "Sandu, you're
going to Moodoo 4." I went I went, "Why
can't we stay together?" They went, "No,
no, no, not you." Then you're going to
four. That was the top top security
wing. Uh they put me there because at
the time I was big. I was intimidating
looking. They didn't really like me from
what I was doing. So my cell was just
like uh oh it's really small, tiny. Uh
you could touch both sides of it if you
put your arms out. Uh the length
not that long. There was like u a
concrete slab for a bed and on top of
that there was like a sponge a sponge
and then you're given a sheet to stick
on top of that to sleep on uh on top of
the concrete slab and then my door is
like you have cages on it. It's got one
door with bars that locks and then
there's another door that locks because
we are considered dangerous and then
some of us we have to go handcuffed
through the door. we have to put our
hands in and then they take you out. I
had fights with people. My hands were
cut. At first when I went in, I was on a
proper downer. Um I got talking to this
guy who could speak a little bit of
English. He used to smoke heroin. Uh so
I started to smoke heroin as well when I
first went in just to get my mind out of
where it was. I needed that escapism and
heroin took me out of there. There was
only about 40 heads of my jail. There
was four Germans there for kidnap
[snorts] and they had a bit of a gang.
Russians were there, about three or four
of them. The South Americans, they all
stuck together. I didn't know the
language. I was on the come down off the
steroids. They were all leaving my body
now. I was feeling angry myself. Uh I
was like getting smaller. I was on
heroin. Um my mind was not good. There
was fights, stabbings. I've been
involved in two. I was stabbed there
twice. Um, I stabbed somebody there. Uh,
his cousin later stabbed me in the back.
When heroin goes dry, when it when
there's none on the wing, there's a lot
of aggression there. People wanting
drugs and fights start. I just lost
everything. Um, I lost everything. I was
married on the out. Uh, my wife found
out about everything, what was going on.
So, I was in jail. So, she goes, "Right,
divorce." So, she didn't want me. She
goes, "You're never going to see your
kids again either." I had three children
at a time and I've never seen them as
well since 1998.
I had my chance and I blew it. Blew it.
How I feel about the mules now. Um I
feel bad about the two that got caught
with me cuz they went to jail as well
and and I told them this would not
happen, you know. I told them jail would
not happen. Uh but it did happen. Um I
messed up. I got out of Spain
and then I went back to jail 2003. So I
was only out a year. Um I didn't really
learn my lesson from my first jail
experience. Um uh simply because of the
fact I I had the wrong mentality about
me. Uh there was no rehabilitation in
Spain. There was nobody no counseling,
no like talking to. I didn't get
anything. I think that's why my head I
was still in jail mode. I was still like
talking to people
and acting to people as if I was in
jail. Um because my head was still in
there and I was only out a year and my
head didn't really change. And then I
was back in jail again. I stopped uh
trafficking steroids. The simple fact
the police knew what I was doing. They
knew I was operating. They knew my
links. Um even though I was arrested in
Spain, the British authorities, they
knew of it as well. They were on my
case. And now when I came out of jail, I
got involved in heavier crime. I got
involved with cocaine. I got involved
with prostitution uh with these people I
was working with a firm, a gang in uh
Gates Head in Newcastle. Uh they were a
heavy firm and they were controlling the
whole area. So I gave the steroids a
miss and I moved on to that
which was a mistake as well. I got seven
years for conspiracy to supply class A
blackmail and controlling prostitution.
The seven years I was given, I served
four years. This was in HMP Durham. My
parole date was three and a half years.
Uh it went over my parole cuz I didn't
think I was going to get parole and but
then there was a bit of jail
overcrowding at the time and they
decided to let a few people out and uh I
was one of them who they let out early.
The comparison between Spanish prisons
and UK prisons is massive. Uh there's no
health and safety in Spanish prisons. Uh
there's no rehabilitation
and sentencing there is like
mad.
When I was told uh my body was uh
[snorts] of a 45 year old at 28, um it
was a shock to the system. But to be
honest with you, I couldn't stop. Um it
was like a I I I couldn't stop. Um I
didn't want to go smaller.
But what made me stop was the prison
sentence. So it was after that that um
it all sank in. Uh the come down off the
steroids, the come down off all the
drugs. uh my head felt right. Okay, I
was doing it wrong. I was doing it
wrong. This is a way to do it now. And
but it was jail and the fact that I
couldn't get a hold of the steroids in
Spain that that made me stop. Otherwise,
I I don't think I would have stopped.
I've had my tests done, my liver, my
bones, my um arthritis all been checked
and now I'm back to normal. I was just
like uh on this roller coaster of making
money, importing, importing, importing,
being money, money, money, bam, bam,
bam. And I forgot about everything else
around me. Was it worth it?
Well, no, no, no, no. Nothing. Uh, none
of that is worth losing
family and going to jail and losing your
money. I do regret what I did, what I've
lost.
steroids are more mainstream now. Um,
this is because it's more acceptable
now. Um, social media influences you get
off all these actors. All these actors
are in good shape. They all look the
part. Uh, everybody wants to look the
part now. Um, men and women. But where
do they get them from? You don't go to a
doctor. You have to go to a legal
supplier. So importation is not really a
factor no more because things are just
getting made here now. It's getting made
in England. I believe there should be a
steroid like practitioner and that's his
job. He's got like a pharmacy where he
sells steroids. You can go and you can
buy and you can get advice and you can
get help. The police could um invest
more money into it. Put like a new
agency involved. um
pro maybe like branch out of the drug
enforcement agency maybe to have like a
separate agency what uh concentrates on
the illegal and I'm sure that you could
find these people easily because I can
find them easy enough in the UK um
steroids is not really a major police
problem. They don't see it as a major
drama.
Um so the law enforcement either they
have to um resources get more money
involved in this trying to even like
upgrade it to class B. But then I don't
think that will stop anyone taking it
because people will still take it. So if
you up this up it for it, make it class
A even.
Why do you want to send people to jail
if if all they're trying to do is just
like make themselves look a bit better?
I don't think it's a criminal offense.
Personally, I now have a CBD company,
um, Alpha CBD, that's been going well.
And so, I've been helping out a lot of
people with that. I've wrote two books,
uh, King of Karachi I wrote, which was
the first book, um, which was about the
ster dealing for Pakistan. And, um,
Self-Made dues paid is my second book
I've wrote now. Um, that's my life story
from when I was like three years old.
Uh, and it goes up until the time I left
jail in Spain to 2002.
Hello, I'm Roger Reeves. I was a former
drug pilot and sea captain carrying
drugs. I made untold millions importing
drugs into the United States and other
countries, too. This is how crime works.
I hauled over 100 loads of marijuana
from Mexico and Central America into
California. I did 20 ton loads of
hashish out of Pakistan and 20 ton loads
of Thaiweed out of Thailand. And I was
rewarded for that with uh 33 years in
prison. If I had a chance to do my life
over again, definitely would not do
this. You wouldn't do it. You knew what
was going to happen to you.
I went on to start to work with the uh
Medigene cartel with Pablo Escobar. Oh
oo Choa. I went on down to Columbia to
find some work and I met up with uh Mr.
Robert Davala lawyer from uh Bogota and
he introduced me to some people in Oh
Cho and I liked Jorge. He a nice looking
young man, spoke a little English and
spoke a lot of English. And so he asked
me what kind of airplanes I had and what
kind of of uh experience I had flying
across the border. So I told you I had a
DC3 or B18, a turbo jet Aerander. So he
was impressed. He said, "Well, we got
all the work that you can do at $5,000 a
kilo." Wow.
How many kilos you put on there? He
said, "Oh, 300, 500. That's one and a
half or $25 million for an eight hour
trip." And I said, "Okay, I'm I'm ready
to go to work." So he called his his
partner in Abal Escobar. He was just
nice man. If he shook hands and asked me
the same thing that Oo had asked me and
I told him the what I had and he said,
"Well, we got all the work you can ever
do." Uh we got tons of it stacked up
here and need moving. I went back and
got my airplane and started hauling. So
after I believe I some loads I had $7
million and I thought, "Wow, that did
pretty good." That was just like in a
few weeks. It was so easy. He just say
Thursday and then it'll be there was a
radio station there at El Paco is the
forks of the Magdalina River and uh in
land from Cartahena and I'd fly there
and I'd be at 10,000 ft coming in and
they would have a a smaller plane at
5,000 ft circling. Sometimes we'd be
able to suffer to find it. Then I'd fall
in beside it and then we'd go some 200
miles, maybe another hour until land at
some jungle strip. So I didn't know,
nobody had to know where we were going,
what we were doing. I'd land there.
Sometime I'd leave one motor running and
open the air stair door and they'd be
aligned with a like a bucket brigade and
one of them was in there. He'd stack
each stack the cocaine came always in
duffel bags like the military duffel
bags had a lock on it and they had uh oh
3x's or rattlesnake or something just
like their friends or they got some went
to New York some went to Chicago Seattle
and it just went all over the United
States after after we got it to Miami in
Colombia the they kept moving the labs
the drug labs the cocaine labs further
and further down into the Amazon till it
was stretching our gasoline like while a
little bit of headwind. We might we
might not make it. So I complained to
the the heers of Pablo Escobar and
George Oaha and the the runways got
longer. I landed there one time and so
Pablo Escobar landed in a brand new
helicopter right side of me and he came
over and we shook hands and he had a a
pilot there named Benjamin Ben and he
put him and he said he's going to show
you something.
So we flew north. I didn't know where we
was going and so we went to Nicaragua to
a military base and landed there. He
introduced me to the general or whatever
it was of the people and it was in
charge of it says land here and stay as
long as you want to all day week
whatever you need repairs they'll wash
your airplane fill it up fuel and be on
your way. So that was that started that
and they paid for all that.
DEA didn't even have any idea that
anybody be come from South America come
across the Gulf of Mexico 700 miles drop
down I would slow down and they had
sometime I don't 30 40 50 helicopters
coming in from the oil wells off the
coast of Louisiana I just slowed down
came in with them they just had no idea
that we're bringing tons of cocaine
so that's when I would I was dead
coming up north and the whole world was
fogged in. Uh it just come in quickly
and I didn't have anywhere to go to. So
I came down the glide slope blind into
New Orleans International Airport with a
load of cocaine.
Sit there all night long in that fog and
I was afraid to little car somebody come
around find me. The next morning about
8:00 I couldn't stand it anymore. I
could see the sun coming through. So I
cranked it up and took off. I still had
a mile out about halfway down the runway
and I went across Lake Pon Train to St.
Tamathy Aviation. That was where I was
going to and I could see it broken down
there. So I just pulled the power and
almost straight down landed and it had
scared me.
Scared? Yes. I was afraid for my life. I
thought I might die that night. And I
told I'm I'm hanging it up. So I told
the fellas in Miami, "This is my last.
I'm through with it."
Oh, Roger, please. Please. Well, that
was how they was making a living. The
Colonians that was up there. Don't you
know anybody that will fly?
And uh so I said maybe. So I I asked
Barry Seal. I had met him.
Barry Seal was a employee of mine. I
took my wife and children down to
Honduras. I was looking for a ranch that
had a runway on it. we could buy refuel
all the way and keep my airplane there
in a hanger. We got flights back to New
Orleans who was a a nicel looking man
sitting beside the window. And I looked
at him and I said, "He looked princely.
He looked different. He looked like
sharp." Then they got a little bit
further. They had a little click click.
I said, "He just switched on his
autopilot." The guy in Reno said, "You
you fly these too?" "Yes, sir. I got a
few hours. My name Barry Seal. How you
do?" gave him my address and phone
number. I said, "Come out to Santa
Barbara Barry. I may have some work for
you." We went flying and without air
commander and a hot airplane. He got in
it like it was his everyday forward that
he was flying. Click, click, click,
click, zoom. We took off and I said,
"Show me your stuff." Well, he rung me
out like Bob Hoover, the national
champion.
And I said, "Whoa, whoa, that's enough."
and he cut the engine till we went
flying this way sideways and we came in
called the falling leaf until land
stopped that plane right on it. I paid
him a million dollars a trip. He was
became my friend. I really like Perry.
He told he turned evidence which I don't
blame him. He had uh certain people
strong men in mean Arkansas behind him
in the CIA and when they left him
holding the bag he was facing life
prison. He just cried and said Roger I
can't do it.
Me learning to fly was so ironic. I
learned to fly and as I was learning to
fly I thought that I would be a
missionary aviation fellowship pilot. I
was working the fire department in Los
Angeles in Redondo Beach and we worked
every other day and then we had four
three days and we had four days off with
my little airplane. I fly down to Mexico
and Mario and the children. So I started
in the antique business and it was
really really nice. I was rescuing. I
was the very first pickers out there.
And me and this fellow would go back to
Missouri where he was from. And so I
would buy them and they had other
firemen that would buy them for me and
I'd go back and we'd run a big truck and
bring them back. You ought to go down
and get you a load of marijuana. Said
that stuff's hotter than plant cakes or
whatever. And so he introduced me to a
fell and he introduced me to a man, a
really nice fell. He said, "You might do
it." I said, "I don't know what you
going to pay." He said, "Pay you
$10,000." I said, "Throw some of that
hay in there."
So, I brought it home. It was nothing to
it. Absolutely just nothing. I give it
to them. They give me $10,000 and a
paper bag and I took it home and shook
it on the bed. Marty put her hand over
her mouth and the baby grabbed a $100
bill and was crawling away and it was
just really fun. I went to see a a
lawyer that was criminal lawyer that
took care of cases like that. And I
said, "Mr. Lawyer, here's $100. What
would happen if I got caught bringing
marijuana back from Mexico on my
airplane? He said, "What's your criminal
history?" I said, "I don't have war.
I've never had a speeding ticket. I
never had a parking ticket." He said,
"You work on the fire department there
in Roondo Beach." I said, "Yes, sir." He
said, "For sure you will get probation."
And at the worst, the worst you get one
year, spend four year four months raking
leaves some military base. I thought,
"Boy, I have found my profession."
So, I went and bought a bigger airplane.
I bought one that would carry I could
make $40,000 a day.
So, I uh invited my mother and baby
sister to come out from Georgia and I
took them to Disneyland in my new
Cadillac
like I was showing off. [snorts] And so,
she said, "What are you doing, boy?" I
said, "I'm hauling pot." And she said,
"How much you making?" I said, "I'm
making $40,000
any day I want to go down there." And I
told her what the lawyer said. And I
said, "What do you think, Mom? She said,
"Do you need a co-pilot, son?"
And that's how it was in 1973.
I'll tell you about how I escaped 1974
somewhere along the way. Yes. I was over
in Baja, California, and got locked up.
I had knocked an immigration officer
down. And so, oh boy, I was in trouble.
two little girls and my wife. We sitting
at a little table in the restaurant and
a guy came up with some shoes under his
arm and uh wanted to know what we were
doing there. Papers. He was really rude
and he was looking at my wife very
rudely. I didn't tell me who he was or
nothing. Just said, "I'm chief of
immigration." So, we got out the street
and I hit him on his listener and he
went down. A few hours later, here come
the Marines with their M16s and bayonets
and arrested me on the boat.
and put me into little jail. So, some
children came up and I had candy and
Coca-Cas in the cell and I passed it
through the bars and they they handed me
rocks and I pulled the door out and
banged it till my hand were bloody and I
got it the door pulled down enough I
could get out and I kicked the front
door off of that that jail house and
went through town and got on my sailboat
and got away for a while. They got me a
next spot down
and the second one I was arrested in in
Mexico and I was tortured almost to
death in that prison in a cell there in
Masatlon prison. It was filthy. I mean
filthy. There was one bucket in the back
all about 20 men to use and it run over
and in the morning sitting on that hard
ground on that hard missing that floor
was miserable. Then they took me and
took me into down the back and it was in
a torture place. It was a I was in a
room about 5t square. You couldn't you
had to go angles lay on the floor
and they take me out and beat me up and
finally I um they put my head under
water, gaseous water. And I mean if you
take a whiff of that, you will explode.
So they hit they beat me from the bottom
of my feet to the top of my head.
And I don't know how long I was back
there. You couldn't tell day or night.
It had a light in there. It was really
hot. I think it was July. And I there
was little little spot maybe that much.
I put my head face under that door. It
was so fresh air. And I went to sleep.
And uh when I did, I had the most vivid
visions or dreams. The animals and pink
flying fish. They were just with their
wings on flying all over. I know where
Disney got his. He was on for my ride.
So, I uh I passed out and the next thing
I knew I was in the hospital with a with
a doctor over me telling me to breathe
and my wife got some money to somebody
and by 3:00 in the morning I was laying
on the cement floor and they shook me
awake and took me through a little tiny
back door of the prison and uh put me in
a pickup truck and wh me away so that it
wasn't escape but it was paid to get
out.
I hold over a 100 loads within my
airplane from Mexico and Central America
into the United States. I was hauling uh
hauling marijuana out of the place
called Pichil Linki and uh just about 50
miles north of Mazatlan.
It was a poor poverty little village and
starving donkeys and had a little tiny
short runway there, 900 ft long. It took
all I could do to get off empty. I had
assessment 207th largeman. So just as I
cranked the engine up,
I thought I blew a tire out. I was
looking and Pedro was punching me
saying, "Policia, police, police." And
it dawned on me. Uh-oh. And I just
pushed the throttle to the firewall and
I went tearing off down that little
dusty strip only about 400 ft in front
of me. And when I got right to the end
of it, they just uh it was on both sides
of the runway. They just riddled that
airplane with bullets. Later on they
counted 80 bullet holes that went in
there and here I am sitting in a seat
right up on top of nothing and we jumped
out and uh there was four federalis
coming down the down that runway running
and they were still shooting and a
couple of bullets hit the airplane. Bang
bang reel out. Pedro and I started
running up the hill through the cactus.
There was a old white donkey. She must
have been 30 years old. big donkey. We
jump on that donkey and get away and we
go about I I I understand later on seven
miles and we found a man and he was
plowing a mule and a little cow. Pedro
of course knew him and they talked a
little bit and the man put us in his
house with his wife and a daughter and
about night the man came back with a
really nice young man that spoke
English. He said I'm Dr. Benjamin Soso
with a red cross and I'm from but he
gave us pain pills and tetanus shots and
bandaged Pedro up pretty good. He said,
"He has got to get to hospital. He'll
die with this." And he said, "With you,
they're looking for American pilot
that's maybe dead or shots. The plane
was just full of blood and I must have
bathed 20 times to get the blood and the
dirt and the grub off of me." They
called for a taxi and they propped me up
with pillows and blankets in the
backseat of that car
and we went was going to Guadalajara. I
guess it's eight or 10 hours. I don't
remember. I got on the plane in in uh
Guadalajara, tore up the papers I had
and said I didn't have any. Called my
wife and told her I had lead poisoning.
And we flew to Los Angeles and she
picked me up and took me to Wilmington
to a hospital where I knew a doctor and
he he worked on me.
What was the last marijuana done? The
DC3. That's a big airplane. So, I uh
went to Colombia in 1981 and I was
looking and I hauled a loaded marijuana
out of there, but it wasn't worth the
effort. I was down over a gorilla
territory and the man that had me hooked
up took me too far. I couldn't make it
back. So, we had to go to a staging
place and wait. The gorilla [snorts]
says, "You come here just at dark. Come
here at dark. You can't come here at
daytime. We have military planes flying
this area." We went back 400 miles and
and parked at the the ranch where we had
staged and fueled up and I was laying
under a tree in a hammock and boy two
jets came down the runway just tearing
it up with machine guns. The jets
swarmed a couple couple times and I got
in there and fired it up without even
and I took off without even warming it
up at all. And so the jets got under me
and looked like tracers coming up and 20
20 mm cannon. Boom, boom, boom. Then
they shot the wing up. Then they come
back to machine gun and tail. I had like
10 or 12 barrels of 130 octane fuel
inside the plane with me. And the thing
if one of those tracers would hit that,
we'd have just went up in a fireball. I
couldn't go very fast because I couldn't
get the wheels up. So I put it down in a
pasture straight ahead. And uh the wings
buckled. I mean they buckled and and the
fuel caps flew off. I took off and they
kept the two jets and finally one of
them went off and I thought I got to get
away from these fellers. So I went into
a thunderstorm up side of a mountain and
every time I'd come out from that
lightning and thunder in there. There
was that jet out there with his boom
boom boom. I go right back into it. So I
went back into it, put it up on this
wing and did a spiral, went down and got
out from under it and it got away from
the jet and I thought, "All right, we
need somewhere to set this thing down. I
done my adrenaline's up and I feel
bulletproof." And I said, "All right,
let's let's make a runway here. The
grass is four or five feet high." And I
just make it a half a mile long and just
keep putting putting the wheels down
until it looked like a pretty good
runway.
Those tires, that thing weighs 30,000
lb. They were breaking through the crust
and it was soup underneath. So I just
put full throttle and it wasn't enough.
That big airplane just come and stood
right on its head. It was at 90° up and
then the nose of it just crushed in
towards us and we fell in between the
seats and it stopped as the engines held
it up and I had the map so I knew about
15 or 20 miles away was a was a little
town. So good. We go there and there was
a fact that place looked real nice. We
ordered Coca-Cas around and here comes
these guards, bunch of soldiers with
their guns. Who are you? There was no
police in that town. This was a military
base.
>> [snorts]
>> So I know what an idiot. Well, they mock
us in a house and uh put a guard in
front of the door and he sleep the whole
night and I knew he was asleep out there
for some way hearing or something. So I
stood on this fell's shoulders and I
took the tile off of the roof, handed it
down one piece at a time quietly and
then we called out through the roof and
dropped down on the other side very
silently. And uh I see that there's a a
boat, a dugout boat there and a a long
motor
with a long shaft up side of a house.
And just as it got daylight, I went bang
on the door of the house with a man with
a with a motor. And I told him, I don't
know, give him a money. So we broke down
our boat down the river. So hurriedly,
we put the the motor on the boat, spit
off down the river.
So middle of the morning, he says, "I
can't go any further. where how where
are you? What where's your boat? And we
told him, "Mister, you've got to go. We
we can't go back." So, we took him all
day long to got almost to San Jose
Guavier, run some rapids, and then we
got out and I gave him a lot of money
and told him to go home. We got away
that way. So, that was a
kind of escape, too. It was an escape.
I went to prison in 1982, taking a load
of money down to the Grand Cayman
Islands. And when I flew back in, I was
arrested uh in Miami. And it was for it
wasn't for anything to do with cocaine.
It was all for an old marijuana charge.
So I did two years in prison for the
marijuana and uh had 30 years of parole
and probation left hanging. gave up my
home and property shortly after I got
out of prison. I might have been out
three or four days and I'd heard car a
barrier seal had turned informant. I
don't know how I heard it but just a
whisper maybe he had.
So, uh, the phone rang. Barry's voice
was there and he says, "I'm coming out
tonight." Very little. I I showed up at
9:00 and Barry was sitting at the back
of the restaurant. There's about 20
people in there, ladies. 35, 40 years
old with the leather skirts and their
leather jackets and guys with their blue
jeans. It didn't look like the crowd to
be in that little in that nice
restaurant. So he said, "I just couldn't
do it. I just couldn't do it." I was
facing three life sentences and he said,
"I've told him everything. I've told him
your part. I've told everything." He put
his hands up over his eyes and the tears
ran down between his fingers. He I'm so
sorry, Roger. I just couldn't do it.
Told B. I said these DEA said, "Every
one of them." I said, 'Well, bring your
head, aren't you? Or Jake J Jacobson was
his name. Anyhow, we had some Regal and
got a little pie and and he told me that
uh
uh you're going to need to come down to
Miami tomorrow and testify before a
federal grand jury. If you don't and
testify the same thing that Barry says,
the only place you're going to ever see
your family again is in a federal
penitentiary vist room. I guarantee you.
And I'm like, get out of here, man. So,
I went talk to another lawyer and he
about told me the same thing. Like, you
either going to tell them everything
you've ever done and your mama and
everybody else or or you going to you're
going to go to prison for life.
So, I went to the courthouse. I believe
it's 3:00. I was supposed to meet Barry
and go into the uh
go into court. Said, "Barry, I just
can't do it, but they're going to kill
you, friend." And he said, "Oh, they
won't very for sure they're going to
keep you." So I gave him a big hug. I
believe I even kissed him. I said,
"Goodbye, Barry. They're going to kiss."
So I took Mari and the children. We fled
to Brazil.
And uh we'd been down there about six
months when I was chasing this $3.5
million that they they owed me. The OO
owed me. And I call the fella and he
says, "Oh, I got good news. Good news.
Good news. All our troubles are over.
Barry Seals was assassinated last
night." So yes, all the cocaine charges
were dropped. So now I'm safe. But I've
got 30 years of parole left in the
United States. And I know they're going
to burn me for it if I ever go back
there because what they didn't get me
with the Barry Seals case.
Mayorca, Spain. It was famous for your
marijuana and hashish. So we went down
and went to Mayorca and met Howard Marx.
Thought I had found the the man I
needed. He had he knew people in
Thailand and Pakistan. And so I started
putting up money to hold hashes. Then we
hauled a another load out of Thailand
and uh 20 tons and Howard puts put us up
with unloaders in Canada and uh $7
million to unload us and we took that to
British Columbia and it was being sold
for I believe $1,400 a pound. Guys in
Canada says, "Well, we can sell it. You
don't need to take it down. We can sell
it more year." So they were selling it
and bringing my friend Jerry and Ron 2
million and three million and $5
million. Well, when the other boat came
in, they were all arrested. The the
Mounties were watching them. So, they
kicked in my friend Jerry's door, and
here's two million in the room, three
million in the car. They got a little
key with a tag on it with a
the storage place number on it. They
was5 or $6 million there. So, all of it
was just gone. So, it didn't make
anything. You don't make any money
fooling with Howard Marks. He then used
to pay me $2 million and he just
promptly turned me in straight out.
Instead of paying me, you go to jail.
And that's why I was arrested in Spain.
And Howard ripped me off all of those
and turned me in so I wouldn't have he
wouldn't have to pay. So that's that's
what I got for my dealings with that
man.
I was arrested in July of 88. They had
me hand chuck like this, my hands over
my back, so I couldn't get to the get to
the uh the handcuffs, two leg irons on
me, but to go into the courtroom, they
had to take all that off and put the
handcuffs in front of me. And I thought,
"Oh boy." And I looked around and I had
a a lawyer there, Basone. And I looked
out, I couldn't see any palm trees or
any power lines. I just said, "How far
is it down?" He said, "It's so far
you'll kill yourself." And I said,
"Well, I'm a dead man anyway. I got 30
years in America. I'm wanted in Germany
for something ridiculous. I uh I'd heard
it hired a German citizen as a captain
of the boat that hauled the hashish. So
he told now I'm wanted in Germany for
hiring a German citizen in an
international crime. There's a
synographer over there uh by the window
and uh she was filing her nails waiting
on the judge to come and the courtroom
was completely full. When two of those
fellas went to smoke or some reason and
had two of them on me, I ran and jumped
on her big desk as big as a piano and uh
kicked that window out. I was on the
third floor and I looked down. Am I
really going to do it? And I thought I
may kill myself. It was um 31 feet down
or 11 meters it said. And I thought,
well, I'm facing life. Ain't no telling
if I'm gonna ever get out here. I'm
almost a dead man anyway. So, I jumped
and uh I I hit the top of a car that was
parked on the sidewalk. Was a station
wagon. And the roof of that car went all
the way to the drive shaft. It looked
like snow going up when the windows
shattered and the uh windshield popped
over three or four cars. And I got out
and got away. And I got out of there
like Donald Duck. I could see a tweet
tweet tweet and and and and got ran down
the street and got away. The next day
this speech door magazine said,
"Spiderman escapes." So
wasn't long there a policeman I was
still running and he pe come with his
police car backwards and a young
policeman got out with a shotgun and
came and ran me down and hit me in the
back. I still got a dead spot there that
that itches when it gets hot. They u
arrested me and I was there in a Spanish
prison. They kept me at night with no
clothes on so I couldn't escape. So that
was kind of funny. But uh they took me
to Germany in a military airplane and
put me in prison there and I got eight
years there. And then the United States
was asking for me and I had about 30
years waiting on me here. Then they was
going to extradite me to the United
States. I escaped from Louve
Penitentiary. Now in Germany when you
went somewhere with them or move with
them, they put the handcuffs on you and
one of them's got the Luger and the
other one's got the clip and they show
you the Luger and they show you the
bullets and say, "We will shoot you,
mister, and we go shoot you in the back
if you get away." So that's the way they
handled it. I called the lawyer and told
him, I said, 'I'll give you $10,000 if
you get that cross street down there
Friday afternoon at 5:00. And he says,
"You can't get out of there. Believe
everybody's ever got out of there." And
I said, "If I'm not there, you will get
$10,000.
And if I'm there, you will get $10,000."
And he said, "They make Kitty." And I
said, "Then you won't get the $10,000."
So he said, "That's a mighty bet. Big
bet on your part." I said, "Well, if you
take it." He said yes. And I before I
was going to do it, there's only two
days. I was planning two or three days.
I I still saw those big brass bullets
going in my back. I thought maybe I
would be shot and killed. And I really
did. I mean, I knew there was a good
chance of it. I did a daring escape,
jumped on top of a guard tower, cut
through the bars, and uh almost died
going through the bars, took skin all
off my chest, and oh, it was a it was a
terrible mess. Went out over the fence
and got all cut up and went across the
place. accident. I'm waiting to see
about the lawyer. I can't go to him.
Then I felt the lawyer coming down the
road in his car, blue com. And I yelled,
"Hey." And he stopped and I got in and
it scared him so bad. He couldn't light
a cigarette. I said, "Go, go, go." And
the windows was all fogged up and he
stopped at the gas station. I called my
wife. I told her I'd escape and she told
me to go back.
She was so upset.
So that was quite a quite a journey from
there to Holland to get away from the
German prison. I got to Holland I guess
and and I called the number for his wife
named Elizabeth and she just cried and
begged me to go back and I said leave I
am so sorry. I your husband's looking at
a month three days or something for
giving me a ride. I'm looking at nearly
a life sentence 30 years. I said I I
just can't. And she cried and I said I
am so sorry. And I really was a son of
the $10,000 and they didn't give him any
time. They gave probation and he lost
his lawyer license and he told me that
he didn't even want to be a lawyer. He
was a professor before that I feel
really bad about but I mean it's like
gambling for $10,000. He took his chance
and I'm really really sorry if that he
did thinking that we chugged all night
and got down to Portugal and I waited a
week there and then got a flight to
Venezuela and then uh fly over and then
a bus to the Colombian border. I got
back down to Colombia
2001 I believe the guy asked would u I
take a load to Australia. I bought a
offshore supply vessel like from Exxon.
It's the one that goes out into the oil
wells and it that thing was pristine.
But when they get 40 years old, they
have to sell them. We used to buy them
almost for the price of scrap. So I
bought that one and took off around the
world with it and we went to uh went to
Africa and reloaded it and then I went
back out and met met an old tuna boat.
They threw a ton on it and we went on to
Australia with around the Cape of Good
Horn way down below and right in the
southern ocean and boy some waves that
was just scary you to look behind you.
It looked like mountains. I came ashore
and sunk the sunk the ship and come
ashore in rubber boats and was knocked
into there and buried the stuff in the
sand and uh then were surrounded by
federal police and the military and they
they knocked me in the head with a rifle
and handcuffed me and took me to prison,
put me in life. I was betrayed
completely. the uh people sent me off on
the on the deal and they um had a
informant that was waiting for me.
Federal police all over the place. It
was a,000 kilos of pure cocaine. And the
Colombians never said sorry, never said
a word, never helped my family, never
helped me with it. But the Colombians,
they paid $200,000 for their lawyers.
Yeah. I felt I I'm really betrayed
betrayed. So
the newspapers was full of it. $400
million worth of cocaine, largest bust
ever in Australia. And what had happened
is they had found out about my other
escapes from where they got my records.
So they put me in in the in this
terrible place. It looked like you see
the movie The Silence of the Lambs. It
was a place just exactly like that where
they looked at you with oneway mirrors.
So, uh,
I I got 25 years and I had to do 14
years before I could apply for parole. I
hadn't been in long and uh uh I was
called to the warden the director's
office and he made me a cup of tea. Said
down there in wall and stuff and he
said, "Now, Mr. Reeves said, I want to
just tell you we're not here to punish
you. We are here to keep you. When the
judge gave you this sentence, that's
your punishment. It's not for us to
punish you. If you behave yourself, you
will have a good life here. And I
thought, wow, I got this time in
America, all that, bro. Got a life
sentence here. I may never ever get out
of this place. Like, I don't usually get
upset with that. That a life sentence
for that. That just upset me. So, I uh
thought, you know, I should tell some of
these stories. I should write them down
for my grandchildren and great
grandchildren. posterity people that
never known that while I was in
Australia I wrote a book and called
Smuggler Mr. Jimmy Carter,
>> wonderful president, a great man, was a
neighbor of mine. He wrote a letter on
the uh president United States
stationary and asked the attorney
general if he would consider me for
parole. And it got it started and I got
back home. I was uh D40 boss Shrea and
uh on July the 27th,
2020.
And u I was arrested when I came here
for parole violations where I was down
there um Terminal Island, California. So
I stayed there nine months in isolation
for no charge, no nothing, just nothing.
Never saw a parole officer, nothing. And
uh then I was released
uh April the 26th the following year
after being nine months in solitary
confinement. If I had a chance to do my
life over again, I most definitely would
not do this. I'd have studied my lesson
and done something. Some people say they
don't want their children to play with
my children because their daddy's a drug
dealer. You talk to people and it's like
they you're got leprosy.
Mari held her head up and raised those
children and they they all doing really
well. So she she's the star of this show
and uh really and truly. Yeah. My
mother, brothers and sisters, everybody
was affected by it. Can you imagine
spending 33 years in prison in cages,
being beat and treated bad, and your
wife and children home alone and without
you and crying and visiting you in
terrible penitentiies? No, it's just
it's just it's just unthinkable. You
just would you wouldn't do it. You knew
what was going to happen to you.
>> My name is David McMillan. I have
smuggled over $17 million worth of
heroin internationally. This is how
crime works.
The heroin world is very dark and full
of secrets. Involves hundreds of
thousands of people, mostly down at a
very low level and passing by heroin
traffickers without even thinking about
it. I was a smuggler for over 35 years,
been arrested around about 12 times. All
of my knowledge is through my own
experience.
The three main producers around the
world of heroin have become Mexico,
mostly to serve the market in the United
States. In South Asia, it's Vietnam and
Laos, the remnants of the old Golden
Triangle, and of course, Afghanistan,
which tops all of them in sheer volume.
And that comes from different provinces
which over the years have had sometimes
droughts and sometimes interference. The
Taliban actually stopped almost all of
the heroin production, but they changed
their mind when they saw the money. One
of my first trips to Afghanistan was
back in 79. When finding and making a
reliable contact for heroin is best not
relied upon through introduction because
the person who's introduced you, he
could be an agent for the DEA. So, it's
better to go from the ground up and that
might mean going out to the farmlands,
meeting the farmers. I've traveled out
into the heartlands of Afghanistan and
lived with the farmers for a few days,
perhaps a week. Got involved in
something local, helped with a well,
come to know something about their
lives, and they make their own
judgments. People in the village would
come to trust me because I wasn't in a
hurry.
You don't need an awful lot of opium to
do quite well if you're a farmer. They
get at least $50 a kilo. Now, for a
farmer, that's quite good. The opium
poppy has a big bulb underneath it, and
that's about the size of a golf ball.
The farmers, when it's mature, scrape
the sides of it, and overnight, little
beads of white sap are produced. that's
scraped off to form a kind of sticky
brick. Now that is the opium base that
contains a very very high yield of
morphine 15 20% sometimes beyond the
farmers.
Every part of the heroine cultivation,
processing and handling is done
separately. None of the people connected
with the supply side are really
connected in any group way that you
might expect with crime. They are simple
people in the countryside. You would buy
perhaps say 10 kilos of opium base.
We'll call them chemists, but they're
really just like skilled artisans who
would take that and do the processing.
Now, don't imagine some fancy laboratory
or anything when it comes to that.
You'll see a couple of old tin pots,
five or six plastic buckets, some cloth
for filtering,
some drums of chemicals, oh, and maybe
an old branch for stirring things. The
opium base is washed out to extract that
morphine, dried out into kind of a black
gunk, and then it is cooked with acetic
and hydride. It smells like a really
incredibly strong vinegar. The rest is
cleanup because it first comes out of
that completely brown. There are really
only two types, white and brown. The
brown is the half processed and only
half a strong version. The white has
been purified, cleaned. The brown is
smoked, whereas the white has
traditionally been injected or snorted.
But there's been almost no white heroin
sold around Europe for years. And people
who inject have been injecting brown
heroin. A dangerous thing to do and a
corrosive thing to do on their own
arteries and veins. The police agencies
have their own way of determining the
purity of heroin. Really, there's no
better test than experience. And I can
tell within seconds from the smell, the
texture, and the taste of heroin, where
it came from, and very close to how
strong it is.
I would first have to get it out of
Afghanistan, it's a landlocked country,
and ship through to Pakistan. That had
its own complications across the border
because any kind of commerce there,
whether it's smuggling or not involves a
certain amount of lubrication of the
border area, bribery, everything has a
price. Whether it's refrigerators or
television sets, the smuggling of heroin
is limited by the fact that it can't
really be disguised into looking like
something else. It can be packed flat
into many different objects. In fact,
books uh were often used. The hardback
covers front and back. I suppose I'd
have to look back upon my time smuggling
out of Thailand as the most successful
operation. The quality was right. It was
the big bags that come from the Golden
Triangle where they're in plastic and
they're stamped with the brand name of
the local warlord or chieftain who
guarantees safe passage. I would press
it down and conceal it within the wooden
surrounds of radio amplifiers or piece
of electrical equipment in your inhole
baggage without it being interfered
with. I would make it pressed within the
sides of the wood and veneered around
the outside. Almost all of the heroin
that's transported by air very rarely
goes above half a kilo slabs that get
concealed in luggage or body packed or
even made into the handles of suitcases.
I used to carry it around by myself, you
know, but at least I knew if I did it
myself, I'd be in control of my own
destiny. But I relented.
I found um couers careers were chosen by
their look. That had to pass the first
test, their stability and reliability,
and also their ability to keep quiet
after the event. And that was very
important. I had one guy that was a a
kind of recruiter for me down in Patia
and another one in London. My recruiter
in London was had been kicked out of
Southeast Asia, ended up at a hostel
here that the government used to um try
and resettle people who've been kicked
out of other countries. It was a gold
mine of couriers. Somebody who's not
relaxed and operating out of their own
valition makes a very poor career. I
don't think people always have
completely selfish motives. Um people
who uh have families to support
sometimes consider it. Poverty might
make that final little push. To pass
through airport security, it was
important to know the airport systems
very well. I would spend quite a bit of
time traveling through those airports,
knowing what kind of X-ray machines they
used, what the staff were trained to do,
whether shoes had to come off or not,
how sensitive the metal detectors were.
As years went on, customs teams would be
trained particularly well in detecting
certain kinds of things. They have some
for cigarettes, they have some for
drugs. They would move those teams
around at different times of the day. It
was important to know when that team was
on. I would use multiple passports in
ensuring the safety of the couriers so
that when they left a source country,
they would arrive in Europe and be able
to take out of their pocket another
passport which showed only travel in
Europe and they would have tickets to
match. I got birth certificates for
people who um had died either in infancy
or very young pre-traveling age and then
built up the identity around that and
get them legitimately issues. Arriving
passengers
were told to go to some arranged point
perhaps a hotel in town or a restaurant.
I would watch them and to see if they
had had any problems because it's always
possible that they'd been intercepted.
Then they would be paid off immediately
and the bags would be taken away. Then
it would be put into storage for safety.
I like to think of it sometimes as
looking at one of those uh phone apps
where it shows you all the flights in
the world that are going on. You see
thousands of them. And in a way you can
say that every one of those little
planes has got somebody maybe four or
five people on board who carrying some
amount of heroine.
During my smuggling criminal career I've
been arrested
um around about 12 times only resulted
in four convictions. The first one that
was back in 1981 in Australia resulted
in a 10-year sentence. I'd been under
investigation by Australian police
and I was running couriers at the time.
My own lawyer told me to get out of
town, but I stuck around. No, I can deal
with that. They'll never catch me with
anything. I was sentenced to 15 years of
which I would ultimately serve 10.
There's no law in the trial. anything
can go.
It seems everything's fair. I would say
this, one of the reasons that I think
the deterrent sentences don't work.
Often the super harsh treatment, my wife
at the time, Cleia, was arrested. My
business partner wife Marie was arrested
and they were put in the women's prison.
They put an informer in with the girls
in the women's prison to try and get
some information out of them.
Unfortunately, little Danielle was an
arsonist. That's what she was in for.
She set fire to the prison and five
women were killed including Cleia and
Mari. That was a
I don't have to say it was a major low
point to I felt guilty and so I should.
The police had moved into my house and
trashed it. Every possession I had was
gone. My wife was dead after that. Next
came my time in Thailand where I was
arrested on a drug case and escape from
there. That took two years doing to get
out of that place. Found myself arrested
in Pakistan and that took almost two
years again to get a not guilty plea.
From there I found myself arrested in
Copenhagen and then lastly a little
stretch in the UK in my early 50s around
2004 I walked away from the last deal.
I'd been giving bits of advice and being
tipped for it but uh even that was too
close for comfort. I'd run out of time.
I was getting simply too old. The price
for this is jail time. And I'd promised
family not to use anymore. And also
based on looking back and realizing that
the reward was never enough.
When it comes to the larger amounts,
then it's all by shipping. I've known
people to take hundreds of kilos of
heroin and pack them into oil drums or
even in the pallets of other goods that
are going. So a technique would be to
order some goods through an existing and
reputable firm that had agents all
around the world, table lamps or even
carb doors or or cabinets so that when
it arrives back in the west that's being
cleared as their cargo, not yours.
Sometimes customs will intercept quite
large shipments. People have asked me
would this make a dent in the in the
market. The supplies are built up at
least
3 months in advance. So besides which
the intercepted cargo never amounts to
the total flow going through. So those
seizures though they might make the news
a ton lost here or even 5,000 kilos
there won't substantially make any
difference. The shipment routes for
illegal and legal heroin never overlap.
There the approach is different and the
mechanism is entirely different.
After a shipment comes in, then it's
unpacked, bagged up into whatever form
it's going out, whether it's in bulk in
kilos or smaller amounts, ounces. It
gets taken out to customers within a
month or would be gone. In the early
days, it was so profitable. A kilo of
heroin back in 1980, just personally, I
could get back a million dollars from
that. And this was in Australia, which
of course got inflated prices there.
expected purity was only at about 15%.
So if I took it down to 18% it would
still be considered good. I used only
dextrose to do this but that still meant
1 kilo became four. In the beginning
even put in place a street network
because there were a couple of streets
in Melbourne which were notorious for
it. Then come back to base four or five
times a night and reload as it were.
There's been some changes between say
2002 and 2022. The retail price of
heroin has dropped considerably. It's
now at about its most base level. Purity
is not great, but price-wise, I can't
imagine any factors that would make it
any cheaper or possibly take it up. Is
it more available? It is, but there is
no market beyond a certain point. The
popularity of heroin goes in waves of uh
different fads and fashions. There's a a
solid core of people who are fully
addicted and they don't change much.
Street level heroin is of course not
pure. It would be dangerous if it were.
It's usually at about 15 to 20% and
that's considered strong. The cutting
agents for brown heroin usually menitol.
It's
really a baby laxative. In recent years,
heroin's been cut with a drug called
fentinyl. It's a synthetic opioid, but
it's a very dangerous drug. It's at
least as strong as even heroin. So, how
would anybody measure it out? A very
tiny amount of fentinel is often mixed
with heroin to keep the strength up. But
that can quite often be misjudged and
end up with fatalities. But when there's
a shortage or when somebody's simply
greedy, the retailer can cut it again.
And this can be potentially dangerous
because it will seem weaker and people
will adjust to using weaker and they'll
use more so that when they get what used
to be the standard batch, it'll be quite
a bit stronger and there's a potential
for overdose. But it has to be kept in
mind very few people die directly from
an overdose of heroin. It's usually when
mixed with alcohol or sleeping pills.
It's it almost never happens when it's
the heroin alone that finishes somebody
off and takes them over the top.
There were political elements to opium
and heroin manufacturer and
distribution. Until 1911, heroin and
morphine were available from your local
pharmacy or drugist over the counter
just by asking for it. In fact, heroin
was promoted as a kind of cural. Little
heroin pills were made by Bayer in
Germany. But after 1911, the Harrison
Act was passed in the United States,
which turned attention to addictive
drugs. When the Vietnam War took hold,
heroin became something US troops tried
during their downtime. They took those
habits home with them. So, we have a
legacy from the the Vietnam War. It's
called a war on drugs, but is it really
a war? A war suggests that one side has
got hopes of winning. Drug traffickers
and smugglers know that they won't win
every break. But then again, they don't
have to win to be successful. They've
just got to keep out of jail most of the
time. But still a high price to pay.
From the authorities point of view,
there would never be a situation where
they could walk out and say, "Right,
we've done our job. There is no more
smuggling. How can that possibly happen
when the nature of business is ongoing,
rolling, and it replaces the fallen
soldiers? The authorities could catch
more smugglers by acting on their
intelligence and the tips they get, but
they're capped by the amount of money,
the resources they're given. In 40
years, I've only been taught one thing
that the only solution is to legalize
all drugs. Legalization would require,
of course, some control measures that uh
somebody wouldn't be going into a shop
and without any sensible reason buying
10 kilos of heroin. On the other hand,
to take away that black market, the
control has to be very light and of
course spend some money on offering
services for people who can't manage
their drugs. Different countries offer
different but generally all poor uh
alternatives to heroin and also not very
effective treatment programs. In the
United Kingdom,
there's virtually none. Somebody
reporting or presenting with a heroin
addiction has to take a place on the
list and to get a substitute has to wait
several weeks. That will force them back
into that world. It might reduce the
harm. It'll save them some money because
they've got a fallback position of say
taking methodone instead of using
heroin. There are programs for harm
reduction that are good, welcome, and
and have some effect such as needle
exchange programs or offer safe places
to take drugs. Of course, that doesn't
get them off the drugs, but any of that
assistance is all a good thing. There's
very little that can be done because you
were hoping to make a consistent
standard product that won't risk
overdoses yet won't be so rubbishy that
people will move on to unsafe supplies.
But I don't see any way of doing that
other than legalization. Also, in a
world of legal drugs, there'd be fewer
prison inmates on minor or any drug
charges at all. And that would have the
effect of uh allowing more police time
to be spent on violent crime and crimes
that affect people in a more direct way.
To help source countries, we would have
to do more than simple crop
substitution, which so far hasn't
worked. It's not much better than the
deadly crop eradication, which has left
a lot of farmers destitute.
I was 18 years old when I first became
involved in the drug trade and not much
older when I began smuggling. I can
never say in any way that I've ever been
a victim of anything. I've walked head
first even even as a teenager. I was up
to some kind of mischief selling bits of
uh hash at school, whatever from an
early age. So when I met some safe
crackers and they were retired from
that, well, they were already a little
bit in the local um drug distribution
network with some uh local marijuana,
but they didn't know anything about
importing and it involved travel. I get
to see the world. It seemed good for me
and I went out and did it on purpose.
Something we don't realize when we're
young is that a regular human life is a
short one and you haven't got so many
years. Only looking back on
smuggling business, drug trade
from an older man's perspective, how
plain and clear it is that it is a not
just the danger but is the pointlessness
and the futility of the undertaking.
Since I've been out of the smuggling
game these days, I put up CCTV cameras
which involves a certain amount of
trust. I've also uh written a couple of
books. One that seemed to take for years
because it was involving that most
complex world in Afghanistan and
Pakistan, the troubles there and the
involvement of the DEA that took about
10 years to write. That's unforgiving
destiny. Of course, I regret
kind of everything about the life I
walked into. People ask me why I didn't
walk away from that world after my first
major arrest. And the answer is that I
couldn't imagine a world where I wasn't
running around underground. It didn't
seem to me at the time there was any
real choice.
>> My name is Owen Hansen. I was a football
star at USC and then ran one of the
biggest illegal sports betting
businesses in America. This is how crime
works.
I was in illegal sports betting back in
the early 2007 all the way till my
arrest in 2015. In the illegal gambling
industry, there's close to $673 billion
a year that's gambled. The biggest wager
I took was a4 million on a Super Bowl
bet. And uh eventually once I started
taking bets from the cartel, the bets
became bigger and bigger. It took me to
sober up to realize like, wow, what what
the was I doing?
I was recruited by USC in 1999
2000 for volleyball and I got offered a
volleyball scholarship. Two years later,
walking on to the USC football team. I
was a tight end for the 2003 and 2004
national championship team and I I was
on special teams as well. my first job
interview I had and it was for a big
real estate developer out of Los
Angeles. I showed up with my national
championship ring and he hired me on the
spot. He said, "Man, I want you part of
my team." So, you know, right out of
college, 2004, 2005, I'm, you know,
making almost six figures and I'm
getting paid commissions on any deals I
bring in. And life was good, right? You
that's what you go to school for. You go
to USC for the networking. And uh that's
what I did. I Iworked with everybody. I
had this rolodex and I I would keep
their phone number, keep their email,
and always put it in my mind. Dad's
proud, mom's proud. Everyone's looking
at me like, "Wow, the golden boy, the SC
Golden Boy. He graduated. He's working
for a developer. He's he's going to be
the man one day." And then that
recession hit 2007. And I remember I was
like the first one or two guys to go.
And obviously growing up as a kid, you
you watch, you know, the great movies
like Good Fellas and Casino and
Scarface. So I was like, man, what if I
could be a bookie? I went to my Rolodex
and I I remember my dad had a friend
that was Italian, that was a book maker.
I was like, man, maybe if my dad will
understand the situation that I lost my
job, maybe he'll introduce me to his
friend. And I kept begging my dad. And
finally, I think after like the 15th
time, my pops is like, "All right, one
one meet up with Tony and that's it." We
met at this this underground bar and it
was like a basement. I walked in and I I
give Uncle Tony a Italian kiss on each
side. I said, "I got the perfect
network, man. Let me utilize it." He
says, "Man, listen. I'll see what you
can do." I'm going to my friends that
are now in the NFL. I'm going to my
friends that are, you know, working on
Wall Street. And uh everyone's starting
to bet with me. And uh the first 6
months on one player, this big this big
big contractor, commercial contractor.
He lost a million dollars in cash. I got
paid $200,000 commission. And I went
back to Uncle Tony. I said, "Tony, man,
I'm doing all the work, man. You you
guys are taking 80%." Man, I said, "You
got to let me. These are my customers.
Let me let me get a little more, man."
He goes, "I can't do it." And that day
forward, I said, "Okay, you can't do it.
No problem. I'm going to figure out a
way to do it myself." Yon Porter
Carrero, you know, was my mentor in the
sports betting. He was the boss of Uncle
Tony. He was with Matra Sports. I got my
hands dirty. I flew offshore. I'm
watching uh and I'm learning and
everything that happens I'm paying
attention to because I'm putting in my
mind, okay, this is how I'm going to
build mine when I when I go to Costa
Rica and build my own. You got this guy
moving the lines. You got this guy
answering the phones for VIP customers.
You got Debbie and Tina answering the
phones. Okay, I get it. Now I understand
what I need to build. And they got
busted, I believe, in 2013 under a Mach
Rico indictment for illegal bookmaking.
And as soon as they got taken down, my
network expanded
tenfold. You know, I went to every
customer he had and said, "Hey, Mata
Sports is no longer in town, but Betto
Dog is." And that's when my my company
blew up. Guy flew to Costa Rica, which
was the mecca of sports betting. And I
went to every office in San Jose and and
I said, "Hey, I know you guys do call
centers down here for sports betting.
What do I got to do?" And you know, I
went to 20 different offices and I found
one that was in a town called Playa
Hermosa. I started to pay a service
where I I pay like $10
for each customer that gambled with me.
I started my website called
bettoodog.com. My nickname was OD Dog in
college. So, you get to basically create
your own domain. You get a 800 phone
number and you can start acting as as a
bookie. So, one outfit can manage, you
know, hundreds of different bookies. So,
I started started my my business like
that where I'm paying a weekly fee. And
now I'm the book. So, I'm collecting all
the money. I'm only taking little bets
like $1,000 here, $1,00 here, $200 here.
I was like, "Okay, I got to figure out a
better strategy." So, I went back to
Costa Rica. We ended up setting up our
own office where I had my own people
that were under my payroll that moved
the lines specifically to Las Vegas. And
I had my managers that handled all my
VIP customers that would answer the
phone directly. Hey, this is B O Dog.
How can I help you? Oh, hi, Mr. Drew.
What's your password? Okay, go. How can
I help you, Mr. Drew? So, it was more of
a custom feeling and they weren't
betting with this this per headcount um
site. I was able to start recruiting all
over the United States and uh I started
become one of the biggest bookies
throughout Los Angeles, expanding to
Texas, to Florida, North Carolina and
and I I got pretty much in every state.
I was in illegal sports betting back in
the, you know, early 2007 all the way
till my arrest in 2015. Sports betting
became legal in 2018. It became legal on
a state-by-state basis and it eliminated
the federal ban. The difference between
legal sports betting and illegal sports
betting is is very simple. Illegal
bookmaker usually is offshore, has a
website that's ran through usually Costa
Rica, Panama, and you you call an 800
number or you place your your bet
through an app that's offshore, illegal
sports betting website is, you know, you
put your credit card down, there's a
know your customers um form you have to
fill out and everything's monitored and
you pay taxes on that money. The sports
betting world that I was in, you know,
was obviously illegal. It was offshore.
I would give a line of credit, meaning
that if you wanted to play with me, it
was like an American Express credit
card. You know, I give you say a $10,000
line of credit. That's week to week. And
come Monday, once the last Sunday night
football game is is graded, you pay me
um you know, Monday, Tuesday, or
Wednesday the following week. and if you
don't pay me then uh you know we
obviously have to go to other matters
whether it's you know making phone calls
or sending someone to pick up the money
and and that's what's different from
today's you know legal sports betting
when you you're gambling through like
the Bet MGM or FanDuel any of the big
outfits you now you you put a credit
card up or you deposit cash and that
makes it you legitimate. So the casinos
or the sports books nowadays never have
to worry. They give so much more credit
as far as like free play. So if you
deposit a million dollar then you get
$100,000 in free play. As a as a as a
bookie, you know, we offered the same
thing, but we're giving you a line of
credit. So you have to basically lose
the money before we collect.
I played on two national championship
football teams. So when I would go to a
sports fan, whether you know most people
in the sports betting industry always
bet on football. So I'd be like, "Hey, I
was part of the last two national
championships at USC." I'd show them the
ring. I'd show them a picture of Reggie
Bush and I, Matt Matt Liner and I,
Carson Palmer, Troy Palamalu, and they
would be like, "Wow." And I would I
would use that that network because
everybody that that gambled had some
kind of liking to sports and it was
mostly football. So it was very easy to
pull that card. Yeah. You know, the
clientele business was always a referral
basis. I it always would start small.
You know, one guy would say, "Hey, you
should bet with OD Dog." I bet OD dog.
He he played at USC. And sometimes you
you would get these guys called Wales.
And they'd come in and they're like,
"Man, I was a big line art fan." I'm
like, "Oh, you're line art fan. No.
Well, listen, who do you gamble with?"
"Oh, you bet with five dimes." I said,
"Well, you bet with Bet Odog. I'll
introduce you liner and I'll get you a
signed football. How's that?" So, I' I'd
call Matt up and hey, I need to sign
football and uh hey, where are you at
next week? So, I'd call my customer, my
future customer, and be like, hey, I'm
gonna introduce you to liner. And we
we'd go meet him at the bar or at a
restaurant and and just these guys would
be blown away because I had that kind of
relationship. And it was so easy for me
and get people to switch over to my
site.
My first whale that I pulled in was a a
a general contractor. He was extremely
large in the commercial construction
space. When I was working at the real
estate developer's office that this
contractor would always step outside and
and I would hear him betting on sports,
I went back to him and I told him, "Hey,
uh, I know you gamble." I said, "What if
I gave you 10% off your losses and 20%
free play?" And I didn't care at the
time because I just wanted his business.
And from there, it just was referral
basis. You know, I ended up getting
three guys that were project managers
underneath him at the office that were
making a quarter million a year in
construction and giving me about half of
that in their paychecks. The bets
started getting big right after Matra
Sports got busted. And uh the biggest
wager I took was a4 million dollars on a
Super Bowl bet. In the beginning when I
first started this operation, I was
like, man, I'm going to lose my whole my
whole nest egg, right? And then
eventually you realize the house doesn't
lose. I've never had a losing year. You
know, a lot of athletes and celebrities
chose me because I was very discreet,
right? You you when you're betting and
you're a professional athlete, you you
don't want to be known that you're
betting. With me, it was like you could
go to the country club, have a round of
golf with me, and if you beat me the
week before, I'd be there with, you
know, a bag of cash to give you, and you
you wouldn't have to have a wire, you
wouldn't have to have your wife know.
You wouldn't have a text message saying,
"Hey, you know, here's here's what you
owe." It would just be I was very
discreet and and I made it so it was
comfortable for them. You know, college
athletes, you got to remember I went to
USC, so they had daddy's
credit card, that American Express black
card. I always tell people, we we can
use that for anything. I would have
these guys, you know, put $100,000 that
they owed me on a a Home Depot um
charge. That would be, you know,
$100,000 in in material I have for a
real estate project I'm doing. So, I
would never turn down a method. So, if a
guy couldn't pay me in cash, I would
say, "Pay me in gold or pay me with a
watch." You know, I can't remember how
many watches I got paid, whether it was
a Rolex or AP. I've even got paid in in
a sailboat. You know, one guy owed me
120,000 and he ended up paying me in a a
catamaran sailboat.
Yeah. you know, as a as a bookmaker,
you're always trying to get an edge,
whether you know, you get inside
information on on a team. Let's just
say, for instance, that UNLV's
quarterback's going to be out because he
let's just say he he had a cold and and
no one knew. But if I knew the wide
receiver and he came and told me that
information, I would be like, "Okay,
let's change the odds real fast here.
Let's let's put the odds in our favor
now because we know the quarterback's
not going to play." So you get an edge
and anytime you have an edge in in in
sports betting, it it's it's huge. As a
book maker, uh at a very young age, my
my mentor told me, "Hey, why don't you
see if you know your your old
quarterback will throw the game? We'll
offer him $100,000." So it it happens,
you know, it's just whether it it can be
played out because it when you're when
you're gambling in the division one
sports, you got a lot of eyes on you.
Now, if it was like a smaller school,
like a division three school, then it
would be a lot easier to to pay someone
off. A prop bet is uh a proposition
wager. So, it would be, let's give an
example. If Kansas City's playing the
Philadelphia Eagles in the Super Bowl,
the proposition bet would be who's going
to score the first touchdown? Would it
be Kansas City Chiefs or the
Philadelphia Eagles? Or another prop bet
could be will the quarterback throw over
or under two and a half touchdowns. So
prop bets make the game more exciting.
So you you can have it for specific
players. You can have it for teams. You
can have it for for anything basically.
You can even have a proposition who will
become president of the United States.
Will it be Obama or will it be President
Trump? So that's what a prop is a
proposition wager. Once the system was
in place, um, I realized that I had so
many gamblers betting on sports, I
decided to expand my gambling empire.
And I started to realize there was a
niche for a live dealer. So, I would
offer my clients that were betting on
sports now to bet on table games. In
Costa Rica, I set up a live dealer where
I would have a blackjack table and I
would have the cameras on the dealer. So
now I have my dealer in Costa Rica on
camera basically dealing the cards. And
now as a as a customer, you feel like
you're not getting cheated because
you're playing against a real dealer
that's live. So once I expanded that, I
had a lot more clientele coming to me
now because now they didn't even have to
go to Las Vegas. NFL star who got
indicted on my case, won three Super
Bowls, Derrick Lavell, was was a
gambling customer of mine. Paris Hilton
was one of my A-list celebrities that
bet with me. There's definitely a lot
more, but I'm not going to go into
detail.
I had a manager that acted as like my my
CFO and he would call literally every
every Sunday he would send out an email.
If you lost, he would send out an email
Sunday night. So, Monday morning when
they get to their office, they'd have an
email. If they lost, it would be an
email that says you lost $2,60052.
And you can pay any of these three
options. I had a gold business called
the Goldfells. And I I would give them
three options. They could pay by PayPal,
they could pay on a credit card through
the Gold Fellas, or they could pay
through a banking system. And we had
shell companies. So the way I did it
back then, you know, you had Bank of
America, Chase, and Wells Fargo. Those
were the three top banks. So, I had
these shell companies for each bank. The
guy would get to his office Monday
morning and he could he could literally
pay any way he wanted to. He could pay
right there on PayPal or he could run
his credit card and it would be charged
to gold fellas. We'd send out a receipt
saying that he purchased, you know, x
amount of dollars of gold. And that was
our our strategy. Now, if a guy won, we
would send the same exact email to the
winner [snorts] and we'd say, "You won
$32,000. How would you like to be paid?"
This was before the deposits of cash was
a big deal, you know. So, we we would
allow $9,900 we could deposit in cash
into your account. So, if a guy hit me
for, let's say, $29,000,
he could give me three accounts. So, I
could go $999.99
and pay through the banking system,
which made it easier. A lot of people
would want to meet up in in person. I
would send a runner and my runners would
make a $100 a drop. So, if a guy, like I
said, won $30,000, I'd say, "Hey, runner
A, go ahead and take it to Tony P over
there and give him 30,000." And we would
pay on Monday. And that's what blew us
up because most bookies, what they do is
they go collect from the losers and then
they pay the winners, but they don't pay
the winners till like Thursday, Friday.
But I had a big enough bankroll at the
time that I was able to pay my my
winning customers on Monday because the
reason I paid them on a Monday is I want
them to have the money in the hand. When
someone has the money in hand, they're
more likely to gamble it away and lose
it faster.
Once the bets were in and I've collected
the winnings, the way I hid the money
was gold and silver. My credit system
was all based on how how fast and and
how well you paid me. So, if if you were
on a credit line of 20,000 and in the
first week you lost 10,000 and you paid
me, you know, right away without any
excuses, I would bump that credit line
up to 50,000. If you gave me any kind of
reason that you couldn't pay, like if
you were a slow pay, like it took you a
month to pay me a $5,000 marker, then I
would I would drop your line of credit.
You know, I try to minimize the credit
card transactions because I like I said,
you don't want much of a paper trail.
Towards the end, you know, some people
couldn't pay me with cash and that's
when I set up the the gold company and I
offered a gold service where I had, you
know, private vaults in Beverly Hills
and if you purchase gold from me, I
would store your your gold and silver
there. And if if you if you needed to be
paid in cash or gold, I I offered that
option. So, it made it simple for me
because a lot of guys say in North
Carolina that owed me, let's say,
50,000, I'd just say, "Hey, uh, hey,
Timmy, I'm going to run your credit card
for for 5 days for right around 9,000,
and I'm just going to send you an
invoice for for some gold that you
purchase for me." And that would
legitimize the transaction. Gold was the
key to to the laundering system because
you could purchase gold with cash and
then you could take that gold and and go
to a gold store and and you can give
them any kind of bullion whether it's 1
ounce or 100 pounds and the bullion
company will give you the spot value. So
if gold is trading at whatever that
value is, the gold company will collect
it and then they'll send a wire anywhere
in the world. So that's how I would
launder it. One of the ways I had to get
money out of of a country was was
through bullion. I was in Australia and
one of the the ways that I was going to
get the gold out of Australia was to
research what's the most popular thing
and I did some homework and I found out
that UGG boots are the most sold items
in Australia. And so I purchased, you
know, thousands and thousands of pairs
of UGG boots. And I'd have the 1 oz
rounds and I would take four 1oz rounds
and I would put it in the sole of the
UGG boot and I would tape it underneath
the sole. At the time I want to say it
was, you know, $1,500. So you're looking
at uh $6,000 per Ugg boot. There's two
UGG boots. That's $12,000. And I was,
you know, sending 10 pairs of UGG boots
every week. So that's 120 grand I'm
laundering through Ugg boots and gold
weekly. You have to move money offshore
because you want to protect yourself
from the US government. And when you're
offshore, you you uh you avoid the US
government finding the the money
obviously. So, anytime you can get
somewhere where that that country
doesn't associate with the government or
cooperate with um any kind of illegal
activity with the government, then
that's the the best place to to launder
it offshore. ATMs was key for my
business because when someone goes into
a bank, they're not going to have issues
pulling out the cash if they're owner of
an ATM business. So, the guys that are
working for me own the ATM companies.
You know, for TB, for instance, I can
talk about him. He he was indicted on my
case. When he would go in and and pull
out, let's say, $80,000 on a Monday and
a h 100,000 on a Tuesday. The the teller
is not looking at him like he's some
some drug dealer, right? The teller is
looking at this business. It says ATM
Unlimited and he knows right away like
that teller knows, okay, this guy's in
the the ATM business. This is this cash
is going into ATM machines that's
servicing people throughout the United
States when they use their ATM machine.
It made it really easy to to launder the
money through the ATM business because
he was benefiting by making 3% and now
I'm getting bags of cash without any um
eyes being raised. In the beginning, you
know, it was it's it was like a million
dollars a week. And then towards the end
of my my downfall, I would say, you
know, we we were taking in
between 10 and 20 million of bets in a
week. Man, the most sophisticated money
I was moving was was the Bank of China.
The Bank of China in Australia allowed
you to deposit cash at any given time.
They would transfer the money anywhere
in the world you wanted it. So I would
come into the Bank of China with
different IDs and I had, you know, 10
different aliases between me and four
other guys and and the Bank of China
would look at us. It wouldn't be our
name, but they wouldn't know because
they had no clue. And they would wire
anywhere in in the world for us. And
that that was the the key to my moving
my money the fastest. Besides the
casinos, you know, the casinos are the
best and fastest way to launder money
because there's never any any question
because when you're dealing with these
high roller um these clients that gamble
in the casino, it's very common for them
to have money either wired into the cage
or cash brought in um through through
gambling gambling methods.
I was the boss. So, you know, I I didn't
really keep track of what I was paying
myself, but, you know, I was I was
spending, you know, $200,000 a month in
in my uh my parting and and traveling
the world. And my my big thing was
watches, you know. I I I was probably
one of the first guys to to have a
Richard Malay watch back in in 20 uh
2011. No one even knew what a Richard
Malay was. I had mansions in Costa Rica,
Mexico, Peru, um Hollywood Hills. That
that was my uh my vice was was that that
luxury lifestyle, fast cars, and and it
was ended up being my downfall. I never
gambled cuz I was the book. What
affected me the most was using drugs. I
was I was a party animal. I would go
through an eightball of cocaine a day.
I'd do, you know, a half of uh Pirell
hand san hand san hand san hand san hand
san hand san hand san hand san hand san
hand san hand san hand sanitizer which a
hand sanitizer is 2 ounces I would do
one of those every day of GHB um which
is you know terrible for you I would
drink alcohol on a daily basis and uh
not one day went by where I wasn't
wasn't partying gambling and drugs
overlap for VIP better because every VIP
better likes to party so when I would
take uh one of my you know whale
customers on a private jet and I'd fly
him to Costa Rica
What's the first thing he wants to do?
He wants to do an eightball of, you
know, Colombian cocaine. You know,
Colombia is only an hour from from Costa
Rica. So, obviously, we have the, you
know, probably the best cocaine in the
world there. So, when I bring a VIP
customer to Costa Rica, you know, and I
give him, you know, the best Colombian
cocaine he's ever had, and then we we
take him to a sports bar, and I just
gave him the best VIP service of his
life. So, it went handinhand with my
business. When I think of betting and
organized crime, I kind of kind of
intertwined together because the the the
betting world, you know, started with
organized crime back in the the mafia
days, right? The the mob, the Italian
mob. For me, they really intertwined in
in the organized crime world when I
started taking bets for the most
infamous cartel in the world. And um
obviously I can't speak on who it was,
but I started taking bets and next thing
you know I'm I'm not only taking bets,
now I'm helping them launder money
through their illegal activity as well.
And that's where my business intertwined
and I started, you know, working in the
international drug trade.
I had a bookie out of Newport Beach that
worked underneath me and he was Hispanic
and one day he he started to have this
this customer bet large amounts on on
football and he started paying me every
week and it was it was like bags of cash
like quarter million dollars at a time
and duffel bags. And I remember telling
this this subbookie I said, "Man, you
got a you got a whale on your hands." He
goes, "Yeah, I got I got a guy out of
Mexico that bets with me." And I said,
"Well, man, keep him happy. Whatever we
need to do, keep that man happy."
Because I said, "These are like once in
a-lifetime customers." So, I'm getting
these duffel bags dropped off. I'm like,
"Man, whatever this guy wants, you just
let him know. We give him the VIP
treatment. He's no reason for him to go
to Vegas. He bets with Betto Odog." the
subbook. I said, "Hey, whatever that guy
needs, if if if he needs, you know,
Laker tickets, if he needs Dodger
tickets, whatever he wants, if he wants
to say at the Four Seasons and and have
dinner on me, let him know." And didn't
think any anything of it. And then
finally, this this customer of of uh my
my my subbookie, he finally hit. He he
he hit for close to a quarter million
dollars. And as a bookie, you always
want your customer to win. I tell people
if your customer loses every day, every
game, every week, every month, guess
what? He's going to quit. He's not going
to keep doing it because it's not fun.
You can't you can't be greedy. You you
want to be able to give him some because
when you give him something, then guess
what? He's going to lose that back plus
some. So, I said, "Monday morning,
you're going to be there at 8 a.m.
sharp." I said, "I want you to go give
him the duffel bag of his money because
he's gonna he's going to be expecting
it." And you know, a couple days go by,
my subbookie says, "Hey, my uncle really
liked how you handled that payment."
That was my uncle that's been gambling.
He gambles. He's he lives in Mexico. And
he says, "By the way, he wants to talk
to you." And he slaps this encrypted
phone on on the table. We're at Javier's
Mexican restaurant in Newport Beach. And
he gives me that encrypted phone. I'm
like, "What the is this?" And he's like,
"There's there's no microphone. There's
no GPS." He says, "You can't call on
it." He says, "All you can do is email."
He says, "There's three passwords to get
into that encrypted phone." I'm like,
and he he writes me a message and I read
it after I got in three three passwords
deep. And I get in there and he says,
"Wetto, I like the way you do business.
Thanks for paying me." I wrote him back
and then he responded back. He goes, "I
know as a bookmaker, you probably have
cash throughout the United States.
do you think you can help me move some
some money around and I'll pay you? And
then he told me, I need $100,000 dropped
off in San Diego. He goes, every time
you tra every time you drop off money
for me, I will give you 10% fee. So I'm
making 10% to drop off $100,000. That's
two hours away. 100,000 10% that's
$10,000 for a two-hour drive. That's
easy. So for me, I just call Tony, my
bookie, or Ryan, my bookie, or Robert or
Matt. I say, "Hey, Matt, can you drop
off 100 grand in San Diego at National
City?" Boom. He drops off 100 grand.
This guy sends me an encrypted message
saying, "Hey, where do you want the
$110,000?"
So now I just dropped off 100 I dropped
off a h 100,000 cash and now this guy,
we'll call him Elfe, is taking 110 and
putting it anywhere in the world. Well,
guess what? I'm running this big
operation in Costa Rica where I have a
20,000 foot building. So, it would be
really easy if he sends me that 110,000
to a Costa Rica bank account. Now, I can
pay my employees and I have money to pay
for my rent, pay for my house I'm
building. So, now I'm helping this this
this member that lives in Mexico clean
his money and and he needs things done
in North Carolina. He needed a couple
hundred,000. Same thing. So, now we're
working hand in hand. He's paying me a
fee. But, unbeknownst to me, I still
don't know that what kind of trade he's
in.
>> [sighs and gasps]
>> and it gets bigger and bigger and it
starts to snowball and next thing you
know I'm moving all I'm moving money all
over the world for him now at this point
because I was uh making so much money
with the cartel and working for them
this this whale customer of mine became
you know my number one focus so once I
started working for the cartel the
gambling was just like an add-on to my
business you know I had the cartel's
backing as far as bet betting wise they
gave me any kind of money I needed to
take bets
When you're dealing with the cartel, you
know you can be killed at any time
because they have an army of guys that
work for them. They have these things,
these guys called sakarios that are
basically their hitman. So obviously I
didn't have to stress when I was dealing
with, you know, these celebrities or
these professional athletes. But when
I'm dealing with the cartel, you you
obviously got to stress and and look
over your shoulder all the time. I ship
drugs um internationally for obviously
the cartel I work for to Australia, to
Canada, to uh Italy, to Amsterdam
um obviously this is all public record
so I can talk about it um and throughout
the United States. Uh my big focus was
cocaine and obviously we did deal with
um ecstasy
um MDMA and towards the end they were
shipping kilos of China white heroin. I
tell people not one day did I not fall
asleep with my eye open. Like I would
always have one eye open when I slept.
And anytime I traveled with my my my
security guards or my sakarios later
when I started working for the cartel,
you're always on on pins and needles.
You're you're always thinking that
something bad could happen. And yes, I
obviously regret it. Um but it's it's
the path that I chose and I I have to
live with it forever. And I'm glad what
happened happened and I went to federal
prison because I told people going to
prison is the best thing that happened
to me. It saved my life. I can't really
discuss uh business on the cartel
because that would be considered uh
cooperation and that would end up
probably costing me my life. Obviously
the the FBI gave me the opportunity to
cooperate against the cartel and I I
refused just just to save my life and my
family's life. So, I can't really talk
about that on but but I think anybody
that knows anything the cartel obviously
runs off of illegal drugs and that's how
they make their money. It's common
sense.
For me as a as a bookmaker, obviously
you never want to put hands on a
customer to collect the money because
that's when things that's when I say
it's the fan, right? So, I tell people
it's all about intimidation. You want to
put the fear of God in them. I had
collectors that were 66 Samoans that
weighed 30 350 pounds that that's all
their job was to do was to intimidate. I
would show up to breakfast with with him
and I would meet my customer, let's say
in in Newport Beach and my my customer
would be sitting at that breakfast table
waiting and I would show up with this,
you know, 350lb Samoan guy with tattoos
on his face and right away my customer
would be like, "Okay, how do I pay you?"
If that didn't work, I used to take that
ID and that ID would have the address.
So with that ID and that address, I was
able to give that to my private
investigator that was on my payroll and
he was able to take access that ID and
give me everybody in the family's name
that lived at that that location. So
with that information, I would take the
wife's name and I'd have my private
investigator run the wife's name. And
the wife information would be where she
works, um, what kind of car she drives.
And now it makes it easier for my team
to do a little more homework and you
know send a bouquet of flowers. So one
of my tactics was if the husband was
refusing to pay me and just blowing me
off. I would say let's locate where the
wife works, we'll send a bouquet of
flowers to her work and we'll leave a
just a simple message and the message
would read, "Tell your husband it's time
to pay up." And once they got the
bouquet of flowers and they read it's
time to pay up, they would freak out
like what's this mean? They'd call their
husband. I just got a bouquet of flowers
and it says it's time to pay up. And the
husband would get on the phone and call
me and say, hey, don't ever send flowers
to my wife again. Where do I pay? I
said, well, I'm glad you got the
message. And that's how I use my
tactics. You know, I I I definitely say
I regret um scaring people. I do regret
sending one of my collectors
that was supposed to specifically put
the intimidation factor into this
client. I do regret him going to that
house and his only purpose was just to
basically scare the person because the
person would never guess that I would
actually have someone collect the money
and show up to his doorstep in
Minnesota. You know, no one ever thought
I would I would send someone for a guy
that owed me $2,000 and and send a
collector knowing I'm in Los Angeles and
send a collector to Minnesota. But it
was principal because the guy had won,
you know, $10,000 a week before and now
all of a sudden he loses $2,000 and he
told me to me and he's not paying me. So
to me that's insulting because now
you're stealing. You stole the 10,000
that I paid you and now you're not
paying me the two. So, I do regret that
I sent a collector to the guy's door and
the guy had some balls and he opened the
door and he he he he made a threat to my
collector and my my collector ended up
hitting him and that got got me an
enhancement for you know violent
activity uh for illegal bookmaking which
in the federal guidelines it raises your
points and when you get more points you
get more time. You know I got 21 and a
half years for illegal bookmaking and
distribution of cocaine. Now, if that
violence wasn't there on my record, you
know, the time would have been a lot
less. But I do regret that for sure
because I I never wanted anybody to get
hurt in this business. You know, 95% the
the threats, the the verbal threats or
the the bouquet of flowers
or, you know, calling sometimes I had
customers that that were in their 20s
and they didn't want to pay. I'd call
their fathers and tell their fathers,
"Hey, your son has a gambling problem.
He doesn't want to pay. do you want to
pay or do you do you how do you want me
to handle this? And usually, like I
said, 95% of the time the the family
member or the father would pay the debt.
That 5% chance that they didn't, you
know, things got ugly. You know, I I
can't I can't stop what my collectors
are doing. I'm remorseful for what I've
done. You know, I put all these bad
things on the streets and ruined
thousands of people's lives. And
honestly, you know, it took it took me
to sober up to realize like, wow, what
what the was I doing
going to the University of Southern
California or University of Spoiled
Children, raised from a father that was
a construction worker, my mother was a
librarian, you you realize that you need
to figure out how you're going to
survive being sidelined as a volleyball
player. there with an injury. My coach
pulled me over and called me in the
office and he said, "Hey, Hansen, I need
you to work on your arm strength because
it's not as strong as it used to be and
your vertical jump." And when he told me
that, he says, "I'm going to red shirt
you." And in college, when someone tells
you you're going to be red shirted, it's
basically saying you're you're put on
the bench, you're kicked off until you
get better or until you recover. Your
your injury recovers. So that day, I I
just remember like I was so bummed out.
I came to USC to play sports and I said
to myself, man, what am I going to do to
speed up this recovery and I decided to
go to Gold's Gym and talk to the biggest
bodybuilder there and he said, uh, you
want to do it illegally? I said, yeah, I
want to do it legally. He says, "You got
to get steroids." And he starts writing
down these these names for me. And he
goes, "They're really expensive." And he
says, "Well, I suggest if you don't have
money, you can go to the veterinarian in
Tijana." I had my grandfather's car,
1989 Toyota Camry, and I got in that car
and I drove to the Tijana border. Pull
up to the pharmacy and I I knew I was at
the right spot because there's like six
bodybuilders in there, just big dudes.
And I was like, "Okay, this is the
spot." And I go in there and I I slap
the the list of names on there and the
lady's just marking it off. We got that,
we got that. And I'll never forget, she
gives it to me and I'm thinking to
myself, okay, how am I going to get
these things back? You know, I got all
these steroids. I can't just walk across
the border back with them. They're gonna
stop me. I saw there was some some gauze
and some medical tape that was near the
bathroom. And I said, "Do you mind if I
use your restroom?" She's like, "Yeah,
yeah, go ahead." I said, "Can I purchase
some of the gauze and medical tape?" And
she's like, "Yeah, yeah, go ahead." So,
I go in the bathroom and I I drop my
drawers and I got my compressor shorts
on from from my USC volleyball days. And
I I drop those and I just start taping
up all these steroids, the vials, and
making it, you know, long. And and I'm
like, "Okay, how am I going to fit it?
I'm going to have to fit it in my crack.
Okay. And then the pills. Okay, I'm
going to wrap those around my legs." And
I wanted everything to look as small and
compact as possible. And I I remember
putting my compressor shorts on and
going, "All right, let's go." I walked
across the bridge back to the US side
and you get stopped by customs and they
ask you, "Are you bringing anything
back?" They said, "What were you doing
in Mexico?" And my heart dropped like
I'm about to lie to this guy, right? I'm
like, "I was um at Papa and Beer. We
were you having some some drinks and
some tacos." He says, "Welcome back to
America." And he went like this.
My heart just was like, "Wow, what a
rush." And I to this day, every time I
tell the story, I still get goosebumps
thinking about that that feeling you
have that you just broke the law and you
just beat the system. And from that day
forward, I was like, "Okay, I'm going to
do this for the rest of my life."
Because that rush was what I kept
chasing and chasing and chasing until it
get got bigger and bigger and bigger,
which led to my downfall.
My first official hustle became once I
got back to USC from smuggling those
steroids. I just started taking them and
people saw me blowing up and they're
like, "Wow, what are you taking?" I had
guys on the football team asking me and
I said, "I'm taking decadorabolan. I'm
taking sustenon 250. I'm taking
Winstrol. I'm taking an I'm just listing
these names. They're like, "Man, we want
to look like you." Like, "Okay, well, I
got this bottle for 300. I got these
pills for 400. I got this HGH for
a,000." And I said, "What do you guys
want?" And that was started to become my
hustle. And I I would go down to Mexico
every week and and smuggle more steroids
back and provide it to the athletes that
were all throughout the USC campus. And
that was that was my motivation to keep
up with the Joneses, be able to afford,
you know, dinner out with some cute
sorority girls and and and live life
like everyone else is living there. The
demand was high. You know, it was it was
a thing where every week I was I was
taking that Toyota Camry and and driving
to the Tijana border, parking at Jock in
the Box and and walking across and the
bigger I got, the more baggy clothes I
had to wear because I had to cover up
the size I had. And I I remember I up
one one summer I had a I had this
Quicksilver sweatshirt on and it was
summertime and it was like a double XL,
but it it covered my muscles because at
this point I was I was big. I was like
240 lbs.
And the same question was asked, "What
were you doing in Mexico?" And he and he
passed and he he he waved me forward to
pass me. But there was another officer
that came around. He goes, "Let me pat
you down." Because he saw I was wearing
a sweatshirt and it was 100° out. So it
looked weird. He's like, "Why are you
wearing a sweatshirt in this heat?" And
my heart dropped because I was like,
"Okay, is he going to strip me out?"
Because he's patting my body down. I'm
like cuz if he goes any lower he's going
to feel the bulge and the bulge was down
down below in the private section. So
he's like all right you're good and he
he sent me on my way. And after that I
was like okay I got to figure out a
better way. I started to use my my
network of women that I was you know
friends with and dating and offer them
drinks. And on our way back we'd start
we stop at the pharmacy and I say hey
can you girls do me a favor? I'll give
you a hundred bucks. and they put them
in their bras and in their underwear and
that that started this my my smuggling
tactics. So when I was at SC I realized
that there was a more more of a demand
not only for the steroids but there was
now I'm in the fraternity and I noticed
all these kids are staying up late to to
you know complete their midterms or they
have finals or papers to write. And I
noticed a lot of these kids are taking
what is aderall and uh they're buying it
from like a local dealer and they're
paying $20 a pill. And then I noticed
when they fell asleep, they would take
Xanax to help them fall asleep because
they were so wired from the aderal. So I
was like, "Okay, I know I can probably
get that down there." So I started to
drive to Mexico and start picking up the
aderal, the Xanax, the Valiums, the
Somas. And now I became this this black
market concier where I was providing
everything from from
performance-enhancing drugs for the
athletes to Xanax and Adderal for for
the guys that were in the fraternity or
the sorty girls that are staying up. And
that became my my new hustle. And it was
the markup was ridiculous. I was paying
I believe a 50 cents for a Xanax 2
milligram and we were selling them for
$5. So it's a,000% markup and it's it's
something small and compact and I can
easily transport it across the border
and it's only a 2-hour drive from USC.
So it workked well.
The moment I thought I went too far was
the day
I knew that I was working for the
cartel, but I continued to work for them
because I was making a million dollars a
day in cash. When I lost cartel money,
it changed my life forever because now I
became indebted to the cartel.
And that's where you have to watch the
documentary to see what happens. I
nearly spent 10 years in federal prison.
[sighs]
I was sentenced to 21 and a half years
for racketeering and illegal drug
distribution.
I served my federal prison time FCI Lamp
Victorville FCI and FCI Englewood,
Colorado. Uh the United States
government forfeited a asset forfeitter
of $5 million including millions of
dollars of bullion, four homes, three
Range Rovers, a Porsche Panamera, and a
catamaran sailboat. You know, I have the
next 10 years under federal probation
and uh every month I'm checking in doing
a a urine analysis at UA. Um I have to
meet up with my probation officer uh
weekly and give them reports for every
kind of transaction I do for banking,
any kind of money I spend. So, it's it's
it's difficult, but you know what? We're
going to get through it because it's a
lot easier when you're not doing
anything illegal. And uh it feels good
for once. you know, I was cutting
corners because I wanted to make that
fast cash and that fast cash ended up
costing me, you know, 10 years of my
life. You you decide you you want to go
down that path and you want to be some
some quote unquote gangster. Well, guess
what? Gangsters belong in prison and
you're you're going to end up in prison
one day if you go down that path of
organized crime. My future goals is is
uh to to create something that's the
opposite what I was doing in the past,
right? I was putting these bad things on
the streets and my new goal is to put
healthy treats on the streets. And the
way I'm doing that is I've created this
brand called California Ice Protein and
it's a it's a protein ice cream. I wrote
my book The California Kid while I was
in federal prison and now that's been
released and that's out and um for the
last six years I've been working on the
documentary called The Cocaine
Quarterback and that's uh with Mark
Wahberg's company Unrealistic Ideas. I
had a great relationship with my father.
Um my father was my best friend. He
still is my best friend to this day. And
uh you know the relationship obviously
was was was damaged when I went to
federal prison because your your parents
don't know that you were involved in
organized crime. And uh you know I
remember looking at my mother and she
was very disappointed and my father as
well. But I think they've accepted uh
the fact that I made the mistakes and I
believe they see that I'm not going down
that path again. And and I've changed my
life for the better. And uh I hope
everybody, you know, believes in a
second chance because u I'm a prime
example of of a redemption story.
Before an old bookmaker used to do
everything pen and pencil. So when you
would you would want to bet on a game,
you'd call your bookie and and you'd
say, "Hey, I want to bet on the Lakers."
And the bookmaker would say, "Okay, we
got the Lakers at minus 10. Overunder is
202." So the player would would bet it
based off the line. The the bookmaker
would give you off the phone and write
it down on the paper. That was the old
school way. And then eventually people
started betting through the app on
online, which technology has grown where
it started with www. So now people have
betting apps where they can just bet
directly off the app.
And now it's gotten so big you can it's
called live wagering. So if you're
watching a a basketball game and and you
bet the the game for let's just say the
total was you know over 202 and all of a
sudden you're watching the game and
you're like man my my total is not going
to hit. So now you can you can literally
place a wager at the time of the game.
So, it could be the fourth quarter with
two minutes left and you can still place
a wager to chase and hopefully catch up
to your bet that you're going to lose.
This day and era, I think Bitcoin is
obviously the the number one currency
used for this illegal activity of sports
betting. And I remember, man, I kicked
myself for this one. My my manager at
the time was calling me and saying,
"Hey, this guy wants to take he wants to
pay us in Bitcoin." This was like 2015.
I think Bitcoin was like $50 a coin at
the time. I'm like, "Man, I don't want
anything to do with that cryptocurrency
stuff, man. I don't trust it. Tell him
to go himself. He's got to pay us in
cash." If I truly believe that there's
always going to be a niche for illegal
bookmakers, but I feel the future will
have uh legal sports betting.
Eventually, people will be able to bet
at all sporting event arenas throughout
the United States. Sports betting is a
vice. It's uh it's an addiction. Now
that sports gambling is legal, you see,
you know, promotions everywhere, you
know, um, everyone's getting into it
from clothing companies to um, alcohol
companies and they're all collaborating
together to create a larger betting
atmosphere for for people that are
involved with um, sports. I mean,
nowadays now when you you're watching a
football game and you see a FanDuel
commercial or Bet MGM, it's it's
obviously used to be taboo, right? And
now you see you you're watching a
football game and and you're watching a
Bet MGM ad with Jamie Fox and you're
like, "Wow, I'm going to bet with them."
You know, I I want to bet with with Bet
MGM because Jamie Fox bets with them.
And I think it's so much easier now for
these these bigger brands to get
exposure with all the celebrity base of
people they have that are, you know, the
forefront of the commercials. And it
just generates a lot more activity for
for people to gamble. the offshore
bookies, the illegal bookies are still
thriving because they're giving the line
of credit and and the FanDuels and the
DraftKings are no longer able to give a
line of credit. They have to take a
credit card or some form of payment and
and there's always going to be that that
illegal bookmaker because he's the one
that gives you a line of credit. College
football has changed drastically since
since my days. Now we have the NIL and
guys are getting paid, you know, who
would ever thought college players are
getting paid millions of dollars to to
play the game. I mean, uh, if legal
betting and NIL
existed when I was playing, it would
have been a whole another path for sure.
No doubt. I would have needed to be a
illegal bookmaker and obviously if we
were paid college athletes, I wouldn't
have needed to start the hustle, right?
The art of the hustle started in
college. So definitely my life would
have been extremely different. Even the
the the guys riding the bench like like
myself, right, would would still get a
paycheck and that would definitely have
helped. I I remember reading somewhere
that a third string offensive line guy
was paid like $80,000 through through
NIL deals. So, just imagine if if I
would have had that kind of money back
then to be able to, you know, take a
girl to dinner or or drive a nicer car,
you know, I wouldn't be trying to fit in
like I was. You know, don't make that
right turn because this could happen to
anyone. You know, you you could come
from that same family I came from,
working class, and you you're trying to
fit in with the rich kids and next thing
you know, you're doing illegal activity.
And uh you know, I wouldn't want to see
anyone
serve time in in jail or prison because
it's it's no place anybody wants to be.
It's it's the bottom of of the earth.
It's hell. You're in a 6 by8 prison cell
and you don't see the sunlight for more
than an hour a day and it's just a place
that you never want to go to.
Hi, I'm a producer on How Crime Works.
If you like this video, please subscribe
and comment below with more topics that
you would like us to cover.